<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-31T23:15:28+00:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/</id><title>A Seasonal Magazine</title><subtitle>A lite version of the magazine that will give you a taste of what to expect</subtitle><entry><title>Tool Making</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/tool-making/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tool Making" /><published>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/tool-making</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/tool-making/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-making-of-tools-by-alexander-weygers&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-making-of-tools-by-alexander-weygers&quot;&gt;The Making of Tools by Alexander Weygers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-modern-blacksmith-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-modern-blacksmith-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;The Modern Blacksmith by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-recycling-use--repair-of-tools-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-recycling-use--repair-of-tools-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;The Recycling, Use, &amp;amp; Repair of Tools by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hand-made-hand-tools-by-jbaldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-hand-made-hand-tools-by-jbaldwin&quot;&gt;Hand Made Hand Tools by J.Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#handy-midget-jack-made-from-bolt-and-nut&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-handy-midget-jack-made-from-bolt-and-nut&quot;&gt;Handy Midget Jack Made From Bolt and Nut&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#recycling--repairing-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-recycling--repairing-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Recycling &amp;amp; Repairing by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#clothespin-starts-siphon&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-clothespin-starts-siphon&quot;&gt;Clothespin Starts Siphon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#carbon-paper-is-a-id-in-cutting-wail-bsard&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-carbon-paper-is-a-id-in-cutting-wail-bsard&quot;&gt;Carbon Paper Is A id in Cutting Wail Bsard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hack-saw-fish-scraper-by-harry-g-yocum&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-hack-saw-fish-scraper-by-harry-g-yocum&quot;&gt;HACK SAW FISH SCRAPER By Harry G. Yocum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#country-craft-tools&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-country-craft-tools&quot;&gt;Country Craft Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#antique-woodworking-tools&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-antique-woodworking-tools&quot;&gt;Antique Woodworking Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-making-of-tools-by-alexander-weygers&quot;&gt;The Making of Tools by Alexander Weygers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using tools to make tools is as high a craft and calling as they come. Get your forge, anvil, drill-press, and this well-made book. Start with screwdrivers. Work up to shears. With the sequel below, move on to chisels, shovels, and tools of your own invention.     —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most tools are made of high-carbon steel. This is temperable steel. It can be bought cheaply at steel scrapyards and automotive junkyards. And, once you develop an eye for it, great amounts are found strewn along highways and in vacant lots to add to your own scrap pile. No matter how beat-up or rusty a piece of discarded scrap may be, add it to your own supply. Scrap is cheap, and as rusty, corroded surfaces are usually only skin deep, they can easily be ground clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Files will often remove steel as efficiently as grindstones — generally as quickly, and with greater control. Don’t neglect learning how to file accurately. Make yourself carry out, at least once, the exercises recommended in dealing with hinged tools like tinsnips, shears, pliers, etc. Try to master the filing technique, for it will benefit all you plan to accomplish in toolmaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will sometimes find yourself tempted to whip out a needed, easy-to-make tool that you have lost or mislaid. I have often made a duplicate wrench, screwdriver, hammer, garden tool, rather than spend the time searching for it. The happy result is that wherever I happen to be working — in the shop, studio, house, or garden — there is always a spare one nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-modern-blacksmith-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;The Modern Blacksmith by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ‘ve ever considered learning the Blacksmith trade, you’re no longer safe. If you think that blacksmithing means making horseshoes and little else, you might investigate further. Mr. Weygers’ beautiful book stresses making your own tools and the clever utilization of scrap metal. Starting with a few wise words concerning attitude, he goes on to explain the possibilities that a skill in blacksmithing opens for the craftsman. He continues with explanations of the tools, shop space, materials and basic techniques. He then clearly shows the more advanced tricks of the trade. Every important point is illustrated (by him) with lucid drawings. But the best thing about this book is that it makes you want to go out and Do it. This book is unusually well done, and the author’s spirit of quiet Joy and competence shines through in a way that is rare these days. Now to find a used anvil. . . —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-recycling-use--repair-of-tools-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;The Recycling, Use, &amp;amp; Repair of Tools by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you are an experienced smith, the most recent Weygers book will probably have some things you don’t know; it speaks extensively of recycling old metalworking machines such as lathes and even a trip-hammer. There is a nifty chapter on making bearings, and another on making a good wood lathe from scrap metal. The index shows a diversity stemming from his almost unbelievably varied experience. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the file teeth are not too worn, they can be sharpened somewhat by immersing the files in a bath of acid. The acid seems to bite into the walls of the tooth serration, rather than into its edge, and thus sharpens that edge to some degree. I have successfully used the acid from old car batteries for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Modern Method of “Stropping” Tool Edge&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shop, a cotton buffing wheel replaces the strop. The rim of the buffer is rubbed with a tripoli abrasive compound and the final burr of the tool edge is cleanly removed by it . It does what the barber’s strop did, but better and a thousand times faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hand-made-hand-tools-by-jbaldwin&quot;&gt;Hand Made Hand Tools by J.Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This nostalgic array of shop tricks and other examples of making-do is a monument to American Ingenuity, and is still mighty useful too. It’s all too easy to forget what one did before there was a local True Value store. The book is valuable for the home made tools it shows, of course, but its main value may well be the attitude it encourages. It should see considerable use around a shop or farm. I’m glad I have a copy. —J. Baldwin
FAUCET HANDLE MAKES SMALL “SOFT HAMMER”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ASMALL hammer made of i)rass, copper, or lead is of great value in assembling or adjusting,’  ‘inc machinery. A hammer of (his sort, small enough to be u.sed fur such delicate work as pun rcpairinR, can he obtained without cost by fiitinfi; a suitable wooden handle lo a brass T-handle laken from an old household water faucel.—&#39;. A. L.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;handy-midget-jack-made-from-bolt-and-nut&quot;&gt;Handy Midget Jack Made From Bolt and Nut&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FROM an ordinary machine bolt and nut, a scrap of gas pipe, and a steel ball bearing, the amateur mechanic can provide himself with a powerful midget jack that wilt prove valuable for many types of repair jobs. As shown in the drawing, the jack is assembled by slipping the pipe over the end of the bolt and placing the ball bearing in the upper end of the pipe. To adjust the jack, it is necessary only to turn the nut with a wrench. A considerable amount of lifting power is obtained.—F. C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recycling--repairing-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Recycling &amp;amp; Repairing by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to Hand IVIade Hand TooBs in character and intent, this book is a mostly •still-usefut coHection of down home ingenuity applied to a large variety of situations likely to be found around the homestead. Many of the tricks of the trade are of the sort us moderns are not used to seeing, but with a tightening economy the sort of thinking demonstrated here has renewed validity. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clothespin-starts-siphon&quot;&gt;Clothespin Starts Siphon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tou can use a clothespin to start siphoning gasoline from a car tank, avoiding the danger of sucking poisonous chemicala into your mouth. Pinch one end of a rubber tube between the Jaws of the pin, and wrap the tube tightly over the whole pin. Place the other end in the liquid and unwind the tube. It will guickly fill with gas.—L. W.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;carbon-paper-is-a-id-in-cutting-wail-bsard&quot;&gt;Carbon Paper Is A id in Cutting Wail Bsard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHEN you are ready to cut the wallboard or plywood panels for a new attic room, a closet, or the like that has switch and receptacle boxes already in place Hi the studs, it’s not always easy to locate just where to cut the boles for these outlets. I found in building a darilroom recently that the large number of electrical fittings made this job extra difficult. So I took pieces of carbon paper and taped them, face out, over the receptacle boxes. Then I set the plywood sheet in place and tapped it with a mallet. The outlines of the holes to be cut were then shown clearly on the back of the panel.—LEONARD C. CROWTON.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hack-saw-fish-scraper-by-harry-g-yocum&quot;&gt;HACK SAW FISH SCRAPER By Harry G. Yocum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good fish scraper, which will work better than many bought articles, can be made from three hack saw blades and a handle. Holes should be punched in the blades at different distances from the end, as in the illustration, and the blades fastened to the handle with a thumb nut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;country-craft-tools&quot;&gt;Country Craft Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How didpre-industrial craftsmen make tapered holes for ladder rungs? How did they make round things? In a Just-the-facts, ma’am manner, Mr. Bland ford shows us the tools and how they were made. Clear drawings show enough so you could do it too. Explanations of how to use the tools are regrettably too brief, but you still get a good idea of how they did it then. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ice axe also had a straight blade. The value of ice for preserving food was known from at least the early nineteenth century, when country estates had ice houses (favoured in America) or pits or caves (more usual in Britain). Winter ice from rivers and lakes was used for as long as it would last into the summer. The tool that was used to t r im blocks of ice was two-handed, with a long thin blade and a pick at the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ice saw was used with the ice axe for cutting blocks of ice for preserving food in an ice house. This was something like a small pit saw, but with very large spiked teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;antique-woodworking-tools&quot;&gt;Antique Woodworking Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restaurant owners and suburbanites of the world, take those antique tools off the wall and use them for real work. Here’s how to purchase, restore, and use. And an tiquers, classic work demands classic tools. Nice book. —Peter Spectre&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before a piece of wood could be shaped it had to be made uniform. The gashes left by the saw while cutting the board from the log were quite deep. It was a waste of time to remove only a t h in shaving with each pass of the plane and obviously something dramatic was called for. The plane which was used for this purpose had been developed well before the birth of Christ. In fact, if Jesus was indeed a carpenter, he was also faced with the need to remove a thick chip from the surface of rough lumber. The tool which was used was called alternately a jack or a fore plane.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>Using tools to make tools is as high a craft and calling as they come. Get your forge, anvil, drill-press, and this well-made book. Start with screwdrivers. Work up to shears. With the sequel below, move on to chisels, shovels, and tools of your own invention</summary></entry><entry><title>Good Tools</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/evolved-toolbox/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Good Tools" /><published>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/evolved-toolbox</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/evolved-toolbox/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#milwaukee-power-tools-por-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-milwaukee-power-tools-por-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Milwaukee Power Tools por J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cutawl-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-cutawl-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Cutawl by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#bosch-power-tools-by-j-balwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-bosch-power-tools-by-j-balwin&quot;&gt;Bosch Power Tools by J. Balwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#portalign-by-august-mohr&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-portalign-by-august-mohr&quot;&gt;Portalign by August Mohr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pro-level-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-pro-level-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Pro Level by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#squangle-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-squangle-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Squangle by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#blue-grass-tools-by-richard-nilsen&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-blue-grass-tools-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Blue Grass Tools by Richard Nilsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fas-set-sawhorses-by-richard-nilsen&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-fas-set-sawhorses-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Fas Set sawhorses by Richard Nilsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#xtenda-leg-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-xtenda-leg-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Xtenda-Leg by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gerstner-tool-chests-by-morton-grosser&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-gerstner-tool-chests-by-morton-grosser&quot;&gt;Gerstner Tool Chests by Morton Grosser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tool-chests-by-max-pepke&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-tool-chests-by-max-pepke&quot;&gt;Tool chests by Max Pepke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#snap-on-tools-by-sb&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-snap-on-tools-by-sb&quot;&gt;Snap-On Tools by SB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#solidox-welding-torch-by-sb&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-solidox-welding-torch-by-sb&quot;&gt;Solidox Welding Torch by SB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ampco-safety-tools-by-george-putz&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-ampco-safety-tools-by-george-putz&quot;&gt;AMPCO Safety Tools by George Putz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#leversnips-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-leversnips-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;LeverSnips by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#aushalser-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-aushalser-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Aushalser by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#loctite-technology-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-loctite-technology-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Loctite Technology by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#aerolite-glue-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-aerolite-glue-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Aerolite Glue by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#klein-tools-by-richard-nilsen&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-klein-tools-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Klein Tools by Richard Nilsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pyramid-foundry-sets-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-pyramid-foundry-sets-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Pyramid Foundry Sets by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#vaco-products-company-by-richard-nilsen&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-vaco-products-company-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Vaco Products Company by Richard Nilsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#one-highly-evolved-toolbox-by-j-baldwin&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-one-highly-evolved-toolbox-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;One Highly Evolved Toolbox by J. Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MOST OF THE TOOL REVIEWS in Soft Technology and Land Use are by J. Baldwin and Richard Nilsen. Baldwin is a professional project and product developer, a teacher, and a wide-travelling bricoleur. He has worked with most of the pioneer soft technology groups — Farallones, Integrated Living Systems, Zomeworks, and currently the New Alchemists. He’s worked for Mo^ Tents and Buckminster Fuller. He’s taught design at Southern Illinois University, San Francisco State College, and University of California, Davis. He’s been reviewing for Whole Earth since 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Nilsen is a serious farmer (Colorado, summers) and a professional building carpenter (California, winters). He’s reviewed for Whole Earth since 1973. Both are appalled at how hard it is for the layman to get decent tools. Stores can get them easily from wholesalers but won’t carry them. Lots of the best stuff seems to be available from NOWHERE by mail order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A scandal. And an opportunity for intelligent business. Meanwhile, see “Breaking the Wholesale Barrier” on p. 148. 	- SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that one-shot job requiring expensive and/or uncommon tools, renting is often the way to go. A rented tool will let you do a job yourself instead of hiring a contractor or other worker whose only real attribute is ownership of a tool you don’t have. Pouring concrete is a good example: assuming that there will be one person present who knows about concrete, a crew of friends with rented concrete tools can pour that garage floor at a fraction of the cost of a contractor. Engines can be overhauled, buildings spray-painted, pipe laid, floors refinished .. . a good rental store stocks a surprising array of equipment and associated supplies. These are often biased towards local needs; mud country rentals will include all manner of jacks and come-alongs for instance. Areas where there is a lot of gardening will have manure-carrying trailers. You might be surprised what they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should shop around. I have often found that competing rent-its have very different prices and policies. One may have a better selection than another, or maybe their brand of tool is better or in better condition. Always check a tool for condition, not only to save yourself a drive back to get another if the one you rent faUs on the job, but to make sure that the renter won’t try and stick you for your damage deposit. Make sure damage is noted on the sales slip. Certain machines like ditch-diggers and floor-sanders should be inspected with extra care. I personally run them before acceptance if there is any question. To “get a good one,” it is a good idea to shop early in the morning. Some stores will allow you to take the machine the night before with no extra charge. Don’t be afraid to ask. Sometimes one clerk will be more enlightened than another, and it will pay you to butter up such a person for future use. Get their name. Ask them to save you the good cement mixer for next Sunday. Sometimes you can even talk them into adding a tool you need to their stock. A friendly clerk can also give you invaluable information on using the tool. You should be sure that the directions are complete and that you understand them, but the directions for a floor sander rarely include the advice necessary to prevent the fatal WHAP! flup-flup-flup of the sandpaper breaking that costs you a buck each time it happens. (Pound in all the nail heads first, or they catch the paper.) In the case of a sander, the paper costs can far exceed the rental fee, so watch out when figuring the savings of do-it-yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ll be needing the tool often, it will probably pay to buy it. This would be true for car tuning equipment. For the cost of one professional tuneup you can purchase a set of reasonably good tuning instruments and the instruction book. Have a friend supervise the first time you use ‘em and from then on you’re saving money. Even in this example, though, it may pay to rent the equipment first time around. That way you can try out different brand names without actually buying, and you can also sample the idea of whether you really want to be your own mechanic. Renting also allows you to use a tool of better quality than you could otherwise afford. 
If renting is still more costly than you’d like, consider sharing the rental with a neighbor; schedule your jobs together. (But bear in mind that your name on the contract makes you liable for damage if your neighbor blows it.) Renting together can also save money by reducing the time a tool sleeps while nonetheless being charged for. For instance, you sand your kitchen counter and while the first coat of varnish dries, your friends sand their boat deck. By the time you are ready for the second coat, the sander is back to you again. Like that. It is well to overestimate the time jobs take, especially if you are not adept. Your rental store can usually give you a good estimate of time, assuming they are honest. They’ve had many customers like yourself. They are in business to serve you and can’t take the chance of getting a bad reputation. Usually. With a bit of good sense you should be able to do well, save yourself some money, and be just a bit more independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;milwaukee-power-tools-por-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Milwaukee Power Tools por J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a serious user of drills, saws and grinders or any of a fiost of ottter electric hand tools, Milwaukee is a good way to go. Everything they make is heavy duty, and some of their offerings have achieved the enviable ultimate accolade: their names have become THE name for the tool. Hole Hawg and Sawzall are two that come to mind. Many of their tools have a nifty cord that snaps out of the handle so you can put the drill to bed without having to roll the cord around it into the inevitable snake tangle. Much of their line is double-insulated making it safer to use under poor conditions. There are other worthy domestic brands but Milwaukee is my favorite. Expensive and worth every penny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cutawl-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Cutawl by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtually every display and exhibit shop has one of these precision woodpeckers and I have used mine for all manner of wonderful and occasionally bizarre purposes. The thing can be guided so accurately that it is actually reasonable to cut lacework out of Masonite or thin metal. They come with a grand assortment of blades: the knife blades can be used to cut cloth patterns, tiny saws will deal with allcuttable metals, chisels cut cardboard (leaving a beveled edge!) for gaskets and display work, lea ther, plexiglas, formica, contour models, etc. It’s sort of like a sabresaw in its uses, but much easier to control. The edge it leaves usually requires no finishing — it’s that good. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bosch-power-tools-by-j-balwin&quot;&gt;Bosch Power Tools by J. Balwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ultimate in heavy duty electric hand tools. Many rental stores rent Bosch for good reason: they last. Some of their tools are the very best available anywhere, the orbital-action jigsaw being a famous example. Costing up to three times more than a domestic industrial saw, it can do things, easily, that no other can. For instance, I once cut an 8 inch round hole in the side of a huge K “ thick steel tank in a location that made a cutting torch too dangerous. It only took about 15 minutes! My Bosch drills have been in hard use for ten years without trouble. Don’t be fooled by horsepower or ampere ratings of Bosch versus other brands. Bosch has a good electrical design that uses less juice but puts out more power — their smallest %” drill will wind your arm off at the root if you aren ‘t careful! All of my own hand electric tools are Bosch. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;portalign-by-august-mohr&quot;&gt;Portalign by August Mohr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Control. Until this tool, the only things I had found to give precise control to using a hand drill were those small drill-press type mounts. There isn’t much that those devices can do that this can’t do just as easily. I leave mine permanently attached to my drill. In nearly a year, I haven’t had any job for my drill that this didn’t make easier and more accurate. —August Mohr&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pro-level-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Pro Level by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dial level has a wide range of uses ranging from setting the true angle of a solar collector to accurately measuring the angle of an existing roof so the addition will match perfectly. It’s useful to half a degree, and has a table of rise-and-run on the back. Some models have a magnet so you can stick the level to a pipe or other metal you are bending to a desired angle. You can get one incorporated into a standard carpenter’s level, and in several sizes. I’ve found that the large size is easiest to read and use. You ‘II have to make a box for yours; they’re easily munched in a toolbox. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;squangle-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Squangle by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of giant protractors and angle sawing guides on the market, but the Squangle seems to be the most useful. I’m sure many of you carpenters already know it, but I’ll bet many of you are unfamiliar with the clever device. It makes easy work of cutting roof rafter angles, especially the must-be-accurate “birdsmouth” cuts. When used with the companion Rafterule there’s no faster or more accurate way to make the complex cuts that defeat so many amateur builders. They’re sturdily made with etched numbers that won’t wear off, and plated against rust. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blue-grass-tools-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Blue Grass Tools by Richard Nilsen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Grass Tools have been made at one factory in Louisville, Kentucky since 1840. Their quality is hard to beat and their line of hand tools is very complete. In addition to hammers, saws and screwdrivers, they make tool boxes, cement finishing trowels, cotton and hey hooks, leather • nail pouches, grinding wheels, adzes and soldering guns. 
I have used a 16 oz. Blue Grass claw hammer with a hickory handle for 6 years. It’s the best balanced hammer I have ever swung and I have yet to break the handle. The claw is so finely made that even though the hammer is really beat up, I can still pull nails with it that other hammers won’t get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correctly shaped and balanced power head gives maximum driving power. 
Crowned face prevents scarring of wood. Chamfered edge minimizes chipping. Claw bite pulls headless pins or 20D nails. Long curve of claws affords greatest leverage. Eyes of hammer are forged with double taper on all four sides so that head when driven have a positive grip on the handle at the center of the eye. The taper of the handle matches the tapper of the eye, ensuring a very tight fit on all surfaces of the eye when the end the handle is wedged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Straight grain full octagon white hickory handles are put through a special treatment before driving which prevents any shrinkage of the wood in the ye, thus preventing the handles from becoming loose. Spring neck handle absorbs shock. Swell end grip insures perfect hand hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fas-set-sawhorses-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Fas Set sawhorses by Richard Nilsen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These versatile 12 gauge steel sawhorses cost less than the labor and materials you’d need to make your own from wood. Two styles — the Step-Bench, designed for indoor scaffolding, and the Industrial Sawhorse, which has the great feature of self-stabilizing on uneven ground. Just lean on it, and all four legs are on the ground. Both models come apart for compact storage or transport. Fas Set also makes the Easy Buck, a pair of metal jaws that clamp onto the Industrial Sawhorse and turn it into a buck sawhorse for sawing logs. —Richard Nilsen [Suggested by J.D. Smith]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xtenda-leg-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Xtenda-Leg by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tired of antzy tilting ladders? These legs really do the deed! You can even put a ladder sideways on a flight of stairs safely with ‘em, and that ‘s saying a lot. I’ve been using them for a couple of years now, and can truly say “I wouldn’t be without them.” Sure does beat the hell out of balancing on wobbly half bricks . . . —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gerstner-tool-chests-by-morton-grosser&quot;&gt;Gerstner Tool Chests by Morton Grosser&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you enjoy reading this CaXa\oqyou are probably the kind of person that is seized by an irresistible urge to open all those beautifully fitted little drawers in antique cabinets. You can satisfy the urge in your own home thanks to H. Gerstner &amp;amp; Sons, Inc. ‘ They make superb wood cases that will hold small interesting things of almost any size and shape: machinist’s chests, medical instrument cases,boxes for artists, photographers, dental hygienists, and so on, ad infinitum. The thing that sets Gerstner apart from their competitors is their concern with quality. You can buy a box from them that will stand with perfect aplomb on your Chippendale end table. Their cases are made of polished quartersawed oak, American black walnut, or can be covered with black leather or vinyl. Prices range from $115 to $269 and one look will convince you that their products are a rare bargain in an injection-molded age. Their service is personal and quick; illustrated literature is available. You can get factory seconds at reduced prices (less 20%) too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tool-chests-by-max-pepke&quot;&gt;Tool chests by Max Pepke&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note on the Gerstner tool chests. In the old days, craftsmen made their own tools and tool chests. When they went for a job, they didn’t turn in a resume, they hauled their tool chests in and the boss looked them over. On the basis of the quality of the work, he was hired or not. Tools and tool chests were very personal things. —Max Pepke New York, New York&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snap-on-tools-by-sb&quot;&gt;Snap-On Tools by SB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outstanding very expensive mechanics tools. Considered the best. If you’re professional they’re worth it. Otherwise no. Check the phone book, call, and they’ll send delivery truck of samples. —SB [Suggested by Morton Grosser]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solidox-welding-torch-by-sb&quot;&gt;Solidox Welding Torch by SB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A medium lightweight welding torch that uses pellets for oxygen. Very portable. The Solidox torch is available in hardware stores, home-improvement centers and do-ityourself stores across the country. The whole kit only costs about $30 from say, Silvo (p. 144). 5000° hot -SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ampco-safety-tools-by-george-putz&quot;&gt;AMPCO Safety Tools by George Putz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good tool kit on board a boat is, in effect, a gland full of antibodies the boat uses to fight infection. Theproblem is that a boat tool kit is the second most infection-liable organ aboard (the first is the bloody electrical system). Tool steel rusts horribly. Of the several manufacturers of nonferrous, nonsparking, nonmagnetic (don’t have to worry about setting them near the compass), and corrosionresistant tools, here’s AMPCO. No sparks means no unscheduled explosions. —George Putz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leversnips-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;LeverSnips by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking my prize for the Tool Most Improved Over The Traditional Type, these “tin snips” are so much better than others that it’s hard to believe that the old kind still sells at all. The secret is in a weird twist in the blade that lets you slide the tool along under the metal without contorting the work and marring it with wrinkles (and your hand with the Dreaded Sharp Edges). They come in lefts and rights as do other snips. Ballbearing action takes less pressure too. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aushalser-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Aushalser by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh, for those of you that don’t know what an Aushalser is, it’s a device that makes holes in the sides of tubes so you can attach other tubes there without T fittings. It’s too expensive for the average toolbox but if you have to make a bunch of manifold type flat plate collectors it could save your money. The joints are more reliable and cheaper the T fittings. The tool is made with typical German precision. They also make anifty small tubing bender. The tool can also be purchased separately for less – J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;loctite-technology-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Loctite Technology by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mechanics, especially those working on old, frapped-out machinery, will dig Loctite. Anything threaded will stay together and not vibrate loose if you use the stuff. This is God’s gift to the motorcycle fixer. The same company also makes a glop that you can use to make gaskets with right on the part; and for those engaged in putting new bearings in VW transmissions, they make a bearing seating compound that enables you to use wobbly old transmission cases instead of throwing them away. It works. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aerolite-glue-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Aerolite Glue by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aerolite glues are well regarded, and come formulated for a wide range of uses, including sailplane construction, skis, and boats. -j. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;klein-tools-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Klein Tools by Richard Nilsen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Klein is famous for their pliers and lineman’s tools, belts and safety harnesses. They make close to 80 different kinds of pliers for all kinds of applications. Pliers definitely fit in that category of hand tool where spending a few dollars more gets you a tool that not only lasts longer and is easier to use but can also do more things than a cheapo model. —Richard Nilsen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pyramid-foundry-sets-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;Pyramid Foundry Sets by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;/ haven’t actually seen one of these outfits, but they appear to be typical of the breed. This one seems to have a better-than-average blower system. Sets range from 3 lbs. to 53 lbs. and they claim iron, bronze and aluminum can all be easily handled. The ability to make castings adds an interesting capability to any shop or studio. For instance, you can cast duplicates or missing parts of old wind generators . . . —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vaco-products-company-by-richard-nilsen&quot;&gt;Vaco Products Company by Richard Nilsen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A professional Quality line with national distribution, Vaco specializes in screw and nut drivers, solderless connectors for wiring, and other electrical hand tools. Their tools are designed for the person who is going to be using them all day, every day. I like their magnetic screwdriver with interchangeable bits (No. 70035). Spare bits store inside the hollow handle, and they are magnetized, which means you spend less time on the floor on your hands and knees looking for that tiny screw that got away. A variation on this is the No. 70427 — the same idea, but with four of the new TORX bits. These are the new 6 pointed screws — also called Star fasteners — that hold together parts o f many new cars and appliances. —Richard Nilsen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-highly-evolved-toolbox-by-j-baldwin&quot;&gt;One Highly Evolved Toolbox by J. Baldwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our portable shop has been evolving for about 20 years now. There’s nothing really very special about it except that a continuing process of removing obsolete or inadequate tools and replacing them with more suitable ones has resulted in a collection that has become a thing-making systern rather than a pile of hardware. It’s a generalist’s shop; we’re not equipped to produce fine cabinetry or precision machine work. We can manipulate all common materials. It’s orderly enough to permit strangers to find things, but it stops short of compulsive anal neatness. It enables things to get done with less hassle and so things GET done with less hassle. We use it as a threedimensional sketchpad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People keep asking us what tools to get, where to get them, and how to keep them ready to use. Here’s the story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S TAN D IN SEARS Tool Dept, and it’ll soon be obvious that you don’t need one-of-each even if you have the money. Ask a craftsman what to buy, and you’ll get as many answers as people you ask, for each has his own favorites and specialized needs. They’ll all agree on one thing though: BUY THE BEST YOU CAN. And the more a tool will be used, the better the quality should be. Tools used every day, especially electric tools, should be of commercial or production line grade. You usually can’t find these at hardware stores. Industrial supply houses are where to go. Take a friend who can buy wholesale. These tocols will be expensive, so we’d better justify the cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, the best reason to go first class is that good tools are a real pleasure to use and handle. This helps make wor k less labor. The heavy duty stuff looks brutal. It wasn’t made to look good in the box, it was made to do the job and has been perfected over many years. The tough ones have their own klndl of beauty that you’l l see better as your viewpoint gets aligned with reality. Such tools, of course, last longer and are repairable when they finally do wear. They can take a lot more abuse, especially the inevitable overload. They can handle the bigger jobs and poor working conditions that would soon trash cheap versions. And after a few years in your hand, they often get to be old friends.
For tools that get used now and then, middle quality wil l do. By that I mean Sears better grades and no lower. Really cheapo tools are of no use at all, can be dangerous, and often break the first time you use them. They are also discouraging to use, which might even cause a beginner to give up. Our onl y regrets have been not buying the best when we could have. Tools that receive great strain, such as gear pullers, should be super top quality only. If you only need one every five years, rent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK so what tools do you need? How do you start the stash? There are a few basic tools that everyone should have available: Hammer, crosscut saw, adjustable wrench, pliers, screwdrivers (get a set), tape measure, hand drill and bits. Beyond these, you’ d best gather tools as you need them. Auto wor k wil l require a rather complete set of wrenches and a whole boxful l of special tools, some of which are for particular vehicles. Carpentry wil l require another whole group: planes, chisels, etc. Electrical and plumbing still more. Our rule of thumb is if we need to borrow a common tool more than once, we buy one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleamarkets are a good place to look for expensive items like vises or anvils. Absolutely the best place to get a whole mess of tools at once is to keep alert for a widow selling off her deceased husband’s retirement shop. Another place to look is auctions, but you’d better know what you’re doing. You should shop around. Recently in the Bay Area, we were quoted prices varying 50% on a tool we wanted! If you want to buy a bunch all at once, (which makes sense these days of inflation — tools are a good savings account), some stores wil l make you a 20% deal. Even Sears can be dealt with , as the sales people wor k on commission. They and other stores also have unadvertised freight-damaged goods hidden away. These can be good deals, as the damage is often merely cosmetic. Yo u can give a salesman your name (and take his card) and have him call you when a certain tool is on sale or arrives damaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether in a Big Store or private sale, you should critically inspect each tool for condition. These days, many new tools by reputable (?) manufacturers are faulty . Used ones may be worn beyond repair. Anyway, be nitpick y about it; you’l l be living wit h it in you r hand. An d beware of package deals claimed to be a great saving. The “complete mechanics tool set for $450.00 “ often Includes tools yo u don’t need, and may force you t o take inferior items that yo u would be better off picking up individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do about that little voice that whispers, “Bu y one, you might need it someday!” Well, it’s possible you’l l be needing them all someday, but Sears is onl y the ti p of the iceberg. Have you ever seen a real hardware catalog? 2000 pages? On the other hand it often does pay t o get a set of tools that greatly increases your capability, such as a welding rig. Another way t o go is for a group to buy a set of tools for workin g on one particular item, such as old Chevy 6 engines, and then everyone in the group that needs a vehicle gets one that uses that engine and hence those tools, and the consequent parts pile. (That’s being done around here. There must be dozens of 56 Chevy pickups and flatbeds withi n 30 miles.) Some groups get know n for specialties: “th e Butterfl y Mountain people fi x tractors.” Those communities and families pool their resources and buy a set of expensive heavy dut y tools maybe for tractor repair. Yo u have to be pretty mellow to make this work , especially if there is a high turnover of people. But this is a growing trend, and we thin k a good one. It leads t o barter and lessens the need for duplicate sets of specialty equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our shop is known for its versatility. It’s portable — we’ve installed the entire thing in a recycled 20-yearold , 2y2 ton bookmobile nee breadtruck. Some tools like the radial arm saw deploy through hatches in the side of the truc k to be used outdoors. Others fold under the workbenches (which are all the same height t o facilitate handling large projects). Windows are strategically placed to permit long items to be handled in the drillpress and handsaw. Sixty drawers fro m an old post office hold a host of small commonl y used items and 500 babyfood jars are pregnant wit h various sizes of fasteners. An assortment of scrap metal rides in lockers under the chassis along wit h a 400 0 watt slow-running gasoline generator and the welding rig. The curbside body wall unfolds like a camping tent trailer t o raise the floor area t o 12 x 13 feet wit h a folding 6x 7 workbench in the middle augmenting the ones along the walls. It’s been set up in 12 locations in 10 years. It also pulls the 20-foot Airstream Trailer (The Silver Turd) I live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools were chosen for quality and versatility. With versatility goes a handy ability t o wor k in harmony wit h other tools, enhancing all. For example, wit h the drills and vises we have, we can dril l a hole at any angle in just about anything. The combinations allow us to easily mass-produce parts like dome struts or Inkle-loom frames. This gives a nice potential for making money as well as greatly easing tasks that might be as bad as workin g in Detroit. Versatilit y also means needing fewer tools which means less money out , less space for storage, and less tools to keep track of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people, the biggest problem with tools is keeping them together. That was our problem too for awhile, especially at an alternative high school where there were always a number of young people who didn’t yet see that tools are in a different category than other possessions. Our answer has been to take the time to try and give people a good feeling about tools being extensions of their own hands, and that tools are the means to getting good shelter and other desirable results. A French poet (whose name I regrettably can’t remember) said, “Hammers spend a lot of time sleeping. . .” We like to see the tools at work. We show people how to use the tools and encourage them to in turn show still others how. Having good tools in the hand, together with that tasty feeling that comes from teaching somebody else, gives the tool borrowers a respect for the whole bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also have all the tools marked with a colored stripe. This not only reduces arguments on job sites where lots of people’s tools are at work, but it makes it easy for people of good heart to return strays. We put out the word: “Bring a blue stripe tool to breakfast” and we round ‘em up. We also ask that tools be brought back at sundown unless needed that night. There’s a place to bring them back to. This is essential. A casual pig-pen shop just can’t keep its tools because there “isn’t any there, there.” As an experiment, we abandoned our collapsed old bureau toolbox and bought a (freight damaged) Sears (the best for the money) rolling mechanics tool chest like you see in big auto shops. We segregated the tools by function and labeled the drawers. The result is that tools are easily looked over and selected and just as easily put to bed. To our great surprise, we found that this chest caused a drastic increase in the number of tools being used and a similar increase in action. We even found that we were using our own tools more! The neat storage made it easy to see who was missing, but people brought them back much more reliably than before anyway. The chest can be locked to control unannounced borrowing which is always a disaster. The overall effect has been that under very poor risk conditions, both sociological and physical, we’ve only lost about $50.00 worth of tools in 7 years! And this without having to get too heavy or “high school shoppish” about things. In case you wondered, we did try the toolboard-on-the-wall. It didn’t work, and nobody we know that’s tried it has made it work either, though it is nice to see all those tools hangin’. It has not been necessary to sentence anyone to being tool crib librarian either. We’ll admit that it takes some time to develop tool-consciousness in a crew, but it can be done, and peaceably. The tools spend a lot less time sleeping too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a deliberate effort to raise your own tool consciousness can result in some interesting new possibilities in your life. As with most mysterious-appearing phenomena, a bit of learning soon clears things up and you wonder what had been previously keeping you from doing your own repairs and thing-making. Sometimes all it takes is a different point of view.
I Easily accessible, functionally sorted tools also give you a ready familiarity with the tools you have. This has two effects. First is that as you get to know your tools, you gain the easy fluid motions that go with using them. You’re not afraid of them any more, though respect is increased. This makes you able to work faster with less fatigue just as good form in sports often makes a big difference. It makes you safer too. Safety is also enhanced by having the tools where you can easily inspect them for condition, sharpness and rust. We have found that safety is largely a matter of attitude. The closer tools are to being a working extension of your mind, the safer you’ll be. Self-preservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve remarked that tools are extensions of your hands. No mystery there; a hammer is just a hard fist; a screwdriver, a tough fingernail. But hands usually operate according to instructions from head, so it can also be said that tools are an extension of your mind. Looked at this way, the big (expensive) mechanic’s cabinet with all the tools of similar function stored together with high visibility becomes even easier to justify. 1 find it is effective to store the tools by function rather than by name because this is the most useful way to think of the best tool when you are selecting. Hitters, grabbers, slashers, abraders — regardless of what they are called, are there in their places. You take your pick. Often, just looking at them will give you a better idea not only of what tool to use, but how to do the job or how to design the object. That’s a big advantage of the neat toolbox. If the tools are “somewhere out on the back porch or maybe in the back seat of the VW” then your mind is deflected from creative thinking into a hunting mode, and the aggravation can easily cause you to lose your ability to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easily accessible, functionally sorted tools also give you a ready familiarity with the tools you have. This has two effects. First is that as you get to know your tools, you gain the easy fluid motions that go with using them. You’re not afraid of them any more, though respect is increased. This makes you able to work faster with less fatigue just as good form in sports often makes a big difference. It makes you safer too. Safety is also enhanced by having the tools where you can easily inspect them for condition, sharpness and rust. We have found that safety is largely a matter of attitude. The closer tools are to being a working extension of your mind, the safer you’ll be. Self-preservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second effect is that you get to “know” all the tools you own without having to consciously think about it. This makes it simple to round up strays, of course, and it’s easier to see where there are annoying gaps in your capabilities (“we don’t have a lightweight mallet”). More importantly, you begin to think in terms of the tools you have. The eventual result is that you and your entire toolbox and shop become a big, complex tool with many possibilities. You begin to sense what you can do together. Buying tools with overall flexibility of purpose in mind keeps you from falling into the trap of building a one-function capability with accompanying tendency to conservatively fossilize your creativity. This tendency is strengthened as the value of the tools rises, which is the main reason society doesn’t get fast response to its changing needs from large corporations who have sunk enormous capital into shops that make that only. Like fat cars. Once in that position, it’s difficult to evolve at all, let alone without damage or drastic change of form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you begin to build your tool capability into the way you think about making things. As anyone who makes lots of stuff will tell you, the tools soon become sort of an automatic part of the design process. Beginners worry too much about skill and safety, rather like new drivers worry most about jerking the clutch when learning to drive a stick shift. It doesn’t take long before more serious aspects take over, and the manipulation problems fade out. But tools can’t become part of your design process if you don’t know what is available and what the various tools do. In addition to buying tools that I find useful, I spend some time reading catalogs so as to become familiar with tools that I can’t afford or don’t need at the time. Tool catalogs such as Silvo (p. 144) are rather like my cabinet in appearance so I find it painless to sort of automatically file the information away in the back room somewhere. Tool dictionaries, especially of older tools, are helpful too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you are saying about now, “Who wants to get into it that far anyway?” Friends, there are advantages. Obviously, making or repairing things yourself can save you money and time. Well, maybe it isn’t so obvious. Exampje: next time your car breaks down, find out how many hours it will likely take to fix it. You don’t have the time, right? OK, how many hours will you have to work at some job so you can pay that mechanic? For many of you, the hours you have to work to pay the mechanic will be more than the job would take if you did it yourself. Moreover, you don’t have to pay yourself, and the job can be done to your standards and at your convenience. If you don’t have the skills or the tools, that’s what we’re talking about! Doing it and experiment and practice, the easier it will all come and the more independent you can be. Freedom rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultimate is to make your own tools. Tools fitted intimately to you by you. What could be niftier? Blacksmiths are really into that. A good example is found in the books by Alexander Weygers (p. 160). But tools need not be limited to the shop. How about making your own personal canoe paddle? Or your own left-handed kitchen equipment? You can modify existing tools too. For instance, when we needed to make 7-inch diameter pistons for a small production run of giant raft-inflating hand pumps, we reversed the bit in a hole cutter so it made discs instead. The pistons were then easily and accurately cut from heavy plywood with a great saving in time and material compared to turning them on a lathe that we would have had to borrow. Making the big pump’s leather “piston ring” seals proved to be easy after we spent some time talking to craftsmen in a sandal shop. With their advice, we soaked heavy leather discs in Mink Oil and then pressed them into the desired shape with a matched male and female die rammed by our vise. The dies were made on a handsaw modified with a simple homemade attachment that enabled us to cut bevelled round holes with good accuracy. That attachment was also used to make the next batch of pistons, as it proved faster than the disc-maker on the drill press. Tools making tools making tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can hear some of you saying “small production run! Yuk. . .” Unless you are an artist, and maybe even then, you will sooner or later need a bunch of things all alike. Even with only the most basic tools, you can mass-produce things. The precision and complexity of the produced parts is somewhat dependent upon the adaptability and quality of your tool bank, another reason to intelligently gather good stuff. Large scale mass-production tends to enslave both the workers and the customers. The workers are used as if they were machines. The huge capital outlay for the factory means that there must be a huge and relatively steady demand. This in turn means heavy manipulation of public “desires” and almost always involves politics and coercion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small scale production, though, can mean a great reduction in drudgery as well as interesting possibilities in barter. By means of jigs and other simple fixtures that you can figure out yourself, you can be freed from having to measure each part. Hold the piece of wood against the jig and hit it with the drill and all the holes will be in exactly the same place in each part. (See Jigs and Fixtures, p. 163)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve mass-produced thousands of dome struts and parts for conventional construction. We’ve also produced simple looms and the aforementioned pumps (which we bartered for a fleet of rafts and got into the Whitewater river running business), solar collector parts, signs (during an antifreeway fight), toys, boxes, electronic parts, concrete forms, fence rails, adobe blocks, tents, shelving, lighting systems, and model parts, to name but a few. The ability to get on a small production run frees you from dependence on larger less efficient manufacturers, their prices, specifications and schedules. It can be rather fun, too, if it doesn’t go on for too long. “Shop Yoga,” we sometimes call it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it can be done without sophisticated expensive equipment if you take the time to think it all out first. The thinking is the most powerful part. You can actually change some things out there! Maybe not in a big way, but certainly at a scale that you can understand. You will find that as you work, your understanding of technology will increase a bit, and your fears based on ignorance will decrease. (Your fears based on newfound understanding might well increase, but that’s another paper.) In a modest way, you can combat the “machines taking over” by having better control of the technology you live with. It’s a good feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>People keep asking us what tools to get, where to get them, and how to keep them ready to use. Here&#39;s the story:</summary></entry><entry><title>Construction Money Power</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/construction-money-power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Construction Money Power" /><published>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/construction-money-power</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/construction-money-power/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cover&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-cover&quot;&gt;Cover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#editorial&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-editorial&quot;&gt;Editorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#indice&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-indice&quot;&gt;Indice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#page-setup&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-page-setup&quot;&gt;Page Setup&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#page-wide-configuration&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-page-wide-configuration&quot;&gt;Page Wide Configuration&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cover-1&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-cover-1&quot;&gt;Cover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#content&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#layouts-and-content&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-layouts-and-content&quot;&gt;Layouts and Content&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#page&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-page&quot;&gt;Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#editorial-index-page&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-editorial-index-page&quot;&gt;Editorial Index Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#questions&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-questions&quot;&gt;Questions?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cordesign.github.io/3/assets/img/Logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Logo&quot; class=&quot;selfie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cover&quot;&gt;Cover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;C:\Users\vasco\Documents\design\proj1\meta3\website\3-master\assets\img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/capa.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/80901381@N04/7758832526/&quot; title=&quot;Morning Fog Emerging From Trees by A Guy Taking Pictures, on Flickr&quot;&gt;#1 Construction Money Power&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;editorial&quot;&gt;Editorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine is called “3” for its significance (leadership, strength and ambition); It was developed with the theme ‘World Anthropocene’; It focuses on three major themes: Construction, Money and Power. For each block of text in English has at his side the corresponding block of text in Portuguese different text color. Each page has about 300 words and 3 images per page; each theme will have 3 articles; there will be 3 articles sizes: small or large or small; content is arranged in a grid made up of horizontal lines with a spacing of 12pts;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine has a size 45pts 66pts is left a margin of 6cm from the outside of the sheet 3 white lines starting from the margin of the top and two white rows starting margin baixo.Hierarquicamente there is article name and body text. I used the font “Bickham Script Pro ‘and’ Ebrima ‘on the cover and’ Arial ‘inside; the font in paragraphs never varies, and has a fixed size 10pts ‘Narrow’ for the body and 17pts ‘Regular’ in the titles; When the page background changes to a darker color the font color changes from black to color pink and blue to white; there may be meta-text stories aside to distract the reader. The advertising will be up to 30% of the total number of pages of the magazine; the ad support is based appendages on the covers and in the middle, as in scientific journals. The connection between the magazine and the website will be using codes from magazine and recognized on the website as the possibility of acquiring the magazine (digital version) at a more affordable cost of a ‘like’ on facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;fb-root&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;(function(d, s, id) {
  var js, fjs = d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];
  if (d.getElementById(id)) return;
  js = d.createElement(s); js.id = id;
  js.src = &quot;//connect.facebook.net/pt_PT/sdk.js#xfbml=1&amp;version=v2.8&amp;appId=831238363634095&quot;;
  fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js, fjs);
}(document, &#39;script&#39;, &#39;facebook-jssdk&#39;));&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;fb-like&quot; data-href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/noticiaglobais/&quot; data-layout=&quot;box_count&quot; data-action=&quot;like&quot; data-size=&quot;large&quot; data-show-faces=&quot;true&quot; data-share=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indice&quot;&gt;Indice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How 3 is organized and all the different articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;├── Introduction Pictures                       # 1 
├── Construction
│   ├── One Highly Evolved Toolbox              # 18
│   ├── Hand Made Tools                         # 34
│   ├── Antique Woodworking Tool                # 41  
├── Money 
│   ├── Sylvia Porter’s New Money Book          # 43
│   ├── Money, Honey                            # 51
│   ├── The Bread Game                          # 54 
│   ├── On Free Money                           # 55 
│   ├── Robin Hood was Right                    # 56 
├── Power 
│   ├── Freedom Inside an Organization          # 61
│   ├── Of Acceptable Risk                      # 63
│   ├── The Strip Mine Handbook                 # 64 
│   ├── Council on Economic Priorities          # 65 
│   ├── Soft Energy Paths                       # 66 
│   ├── Energy for Survival                     # 67 
│   ├── Energy Future                           # 68 
│   ├── Soft Energy Notes                       # 69 
│   ├── The Craft of Power                      # 70 
│   ├── Acting from gov&#39;t                       # 71 
│   ├── Congressional Hit Record                # 71 
│   ├── Transcending the Power Game             # 72 
│   ├── Thoughts                                # 75 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;page-setup&quot;&gt;Page Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick checklist of the configurations needed for seeting up the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;page-wide-configuration&quot;&gt;Page Wide Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each page is 190,5 x 297 mm for a total of 80 pages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cover-1&quot;&gt;Cover&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title uses the typeface &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ebrima&lt;/code&gt; bold and regular with the size of 64 and 60 pt of Leading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtitle is also &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ebrima&lt;/code&gt; but with a size of 31 pt with the first word of the description being &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Bickham Script&lt;/code&gt; size 24 pt and the rest description &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ebrima&lt;/code&gt; size 9 with 12 pt of leading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every page uses 12 pt of leading and the typeface &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Arial&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titles are regular sized 17 while the body of the articles are size 10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;layouts-and-content&quot;&gt;Layouts and Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minimum of 6p0 of margin top must be kept and 5p0 of margin bottom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are of my domain. Photographs were taken using a NIKON D7000 and ilustrations were made using a Intous Pro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;page&quot;&gt;Page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different text color represents different language and in case of a dark background blue can be changed to white and black can be changed to pink&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 possible layouts for the pages mostly the same changing only the position of text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;editorial-index-page&quot;&gt;Editorial Index Page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is seen at the backcover as having it in the beggining would interrupt the flow intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to buy a magazine or leave a sugestion? By all means &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/messages/vasco.silvah&quot;&gt;leave a Facebook Message&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><category term="jekyll" /><category term="ramme" /><category term="blog" /><category term="about" /><category term="theme" /><summary>Simple Jekyll theme for your blog by Taylan Tatlı.</summary></entry><entry><title>Bulding Design</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/bulding-design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bulding Design" /><published>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/bulding-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/bulding-design/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#house-form-and-culture&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-house-form-and-culture&quot;&gt;House Form and Culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#american-building&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-american-building&quot;&gt;American Building&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-healthy-house&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-healthy-house&quot;&gt;The Healthy House&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-poetics-of-space&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-poetics-of-space&quot;&gt;The Poetics of Space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#learning-architecture-by-lloyd-kahn&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-learning-architecture-by-lloyd-kahn&quot;&gt;Learning Architecture by Lloyd Kahn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;house-form-and-culture&quot;&gt;House Form and Culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A relatively unknown and thought-provoking book on primitive and vernacular forces, culture and materials that bring (brought) about their designs. Valuable and instructive for that critical factor in house design: approach. —Lloyd Kahn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pueblo looks like a land form because the close relation of house form and landscape eflects the harmony of man and nature. The whole landscape is sacred, as is the house, and the whole environment influences all of Pueblo life. In fact, Pueblo Indians beg forgiveness every time they fell a tree or kill a jack rabbit. Corn growing is for them a religious act and an essential part of the total spiritual life. It is this attitude which affects the house, its form, siting, and relation to the land, and helps explain why such buildings enhance rather than damage the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be argued that, if we consider hostility of environment and available resources, the problems faced by the Eskimo are not unlike those involved in the design of a space capsule. The difference is less than one would imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-building&quot;&gt;American Building&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fitch criticizes architects for not dealing with environmental forces. He finds that our highly developed technology and equipment for manipulating the natural environment have led architects to ignore natural forces as a factor in design. Air conditioning has allowed gigantic buildings of glass facing summer sun, etc. This is an important study of what has gone wrong, why, and what can be done about creating a more human architecture, a more harmonious relationship between buildings and their environment. —Lloyd Kahn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-healthy-house&quot;&gt;The Healthy House&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my respected friends has called this book “strange.” Yup, and I strongly disagree with some of the not-very-rigorously-proven assertions. But. But it’s that Old Master of Philosophy of Building Ken Kern speaking, and we know from all the good things he’s brought out in the past ^The Owner Built Home, p. 223, for instance) that Ken is worth listening to. I find the proposals refreshingly annoying, exciting, and I happily admit that reading The Healthy House has started me thinking more carefully about a number of aspects of building. Typical of Ken is that he has built a house incorporating his philosophy: it’s underground, compound-curved, bamboo-rein forced stabilized clay. Egad! Living in it helps protect you from a variety of assaults (some of which you may not have heard of) and augments natural forces that tend to promote good health. Definitely worth a look, especially for the very different point of view. • —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-poetics-of-space&quot;&gt;The Poetics of Space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s been so much written in the last few years about the external construction of shelters. This book is about the house as interior construct, the house of dreams, the “dream house” that we’re always building until the day we die, and the house of reverie which is the house we were born in, our first earthly home where “a lamp is always waiting in the window, and through it the house too is waiting” for each of us to come in, curl up, and dream. The external metaphor Bachelard uses for the house is the nest that the bird constructs with his own body, using his breast for a tool. He (the bird) suggests that a house is built by and for the body, that it takes form from the inside. “This being the case,” writes Bachelard, “if I were asked to name the chief benefit of the house, I should say: the house shelters day-dreaming, the house protects the dreamer, the house allows one to dream in peace.” The county ought to write that into its building code. —Lewis MacAdams, Jr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housed everywhere but nowhere shut in, this is the motto of the dreamer of dwellings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, the corner is a haven that ensures us one of the things we prize most highly — immobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a poet looks through a microscope or a telescope, he always sees the same thing. Distance, too, creates miniatures at all points on the horizon, and the dreamer, faced with these spectacles of distant nature, picks out these miniatures as so many nests of solitude in which he dreams of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-architecture-by-lloyd-kahn&quot;&gt;Learning Architecture by Lloyd Kahn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I did a slide show at a nearby college. A student came up afterwards and asked if I knew of any good architecture schools in the country. I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went across the street for some coffee and as we sat I told him what I’d do if I were him and wanted to learn building design: spend some months reading high-quality books on vernacular building as well as the world’s great architecture. Then set off with sleeping bag, backpack, camera and notebook for a year or two of travel — studying, sketching, recording, listening, learning. Shelter being so basic, people of all lands seem willing to talk about it. They are proud of handwork (where it still exists), eager to show an interested visitor buildings, local ingenuity. Study humble, indigenous buildings as well as some monumental feats, letting circumstance and intuition guide the way. Sooner or later return home, put notes together, develop film, ponder what has been learned. In between travel and study — preferably before — work for a builder; and learn to draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn building you’ll probably have to search around to find someone to take you on. Start as a laborer if need be; you’ll pick up the skills as you go. Keep working on and off until you know something about building. It’s a skill useful for a lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draw as much as possible. Books can be helpful, but nothing is better than a compatible teacher. There might be someone at a college (this could mean a trek from school to school) who would be the right one. Or you might find a job working for an architect: he’d teach you drawing, you’d help him do drafting and get a salary that increased along with your proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study, travel, building, drawing — not in any particular order — could make you into a fine architect, although without the credentials. It could also make you a misfit in today’s western world of building and design, but who knows how long it will all last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have all this together as we sat there on our second cup of coffee, but I’ve been thinking about it since. Because with what architecture has become, it’s hard to learn the skills on a human scale, and most colleges are of little help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess what I’ve done is outlined an alternative (that word again) course in architecture. For those who can’t afford a good school or find one, it would be a vital way to learn the art and science of building.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>A relatively unknown and thought-provoking book on primitive and vernacular forces, culture and materials that bring (brought) about their designs. Valuable and instructive for that critical factor in house design: approach.</summary></entry><entry><title>Personal Finance</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/personal-finance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Finance" /><published>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/personal-finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/personal-finance/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sylvia-porters-new-money-book&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-sylvia-porters-new-money-book&quot;&gt;Sylvia Porter’s New Money Book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-find-the-right-site&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-how-to-find-the-right-site&quot;&gt;How To Find The Right Site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-fund-for-you&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-what-fund-for-you&quot;&gt;What Fund For You?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-should-you-buy-mutual-funds&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-why-should-you-buy-mutual-funds&quot;&gt;Why Should You Buy Mutual Funds?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#money-honey-1980-by-george-von-hikheimer&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-money-honey-1980-by-george-von-hikheimer&quot;&gt;Money, Honey, 1980 by George von Hikheimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sylvia-porters-new-money-book&quot;&gt;Sylvia Porter’s New Money Book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sylvia Porter is not Iddding. Tfiis is about money, not so much iiow to make it but flow to fieep, save, and judiciously spend it. There is advice and information on every purchasing decision, and it is usually good advice. —Paul Hawken&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-find-the-right-site&quot;&gt;How To Find The Right Site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you invest a penny in your dream house you must find the right property on which to build. Here’s how to
go about it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Find out from the town clerk’s office the zoning regulations in the neighborhood in which the property you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• like is situated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Ask for a survey of the lot. Exactly where are the boundaries? (Walk the lines yourself.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Plan to invest in a title search, no matter how little the lot costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Find out from local lenders whether they will make home-building loans in your neighborhood. A good source of information is the Federal Housing Administration’s nearest branch office. The FHA considers the neighborhood as well as the individual house when it insures loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Inspect the lot after a heavy rain; if possible, after several days of downpour. That will show how rapidly surface water leaves the site. If a plot is f i l l e d , the f i ll may settle and take the house along with i t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Be wary of land subdivisions still in the “blueprint stage.” These always are a gamble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-fund-for-you&quot;&gt;What Fund For You?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every investor certainly should investigate funds. Many of you will find the funds are suitable for achieving your investment goals.
To help you determine the kind of mutual fund that is best suited for you, here are broad guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, if you are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Single, earning under $15,000, with a savings-oriented (conservative) temperament: you should own an income fund with a dual goal of providing some longer-term capital growth.
• Single, earning under $15,000, w i th a chance-taker’s (aggressive) temperament: yours should be a “total return” fund, concentrating on high-growth common stocks or a long-term growth fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Married, with two or three dependents, earning $15,000 to $25,000, w i th a conservative temperament: the best for you would be a blue-chip, common stock fund, for long-term growth of both capital and income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Married, with two or three dependents, earning $25,000 and up, w i th a growth-oriented temperament: yours should be either a pu’ a “income” fund, a “moneymarket” fund, or a bond fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Working couple, earning $25,000 and up, w i th growthoriented temperament: obviously, a growth fund is for you, so the investments can help you accumulate resources for future tuition needs, travel and other recreation, retirement, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Older person, income coming from Social Security and some savings, w i th a conservative temperament and a goal of preservation of capital and more current income:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ideally, the medium should be an income fund of the more conservative type which pays dividends and has some appreciation possibilities. Or a money-market fund which will preserve capital and offer a satisfactory yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-should-you-buy-mutual-funds&quot;&gt;Why Should You Buy Mutual Funds?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to tell you that the investment advice given to the small investor in the United States is far inferior to that given to the big guy, and that the men and women who give that advice agree the above is true, wouldn’t you be deeply disturbed? Okay, I’m telling you that this is the opinion of an overwhelming percentage of the nation’s security analysts. According to a recent survey:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• A shocking seven out of ten security analysts have “reservations about the advice available to the small investor as compared with that given the large one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Only one in three believes that “the quality of investment advice now available adequately serves all types of investors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Nearly half favor “some form of blanket registration of security analysts” (in short, greater control).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M ORE IMPORTANT MISTAKES A RE made about personal finance ~ about money in general — than maybe any other easily correctable area of human folly. It’s one of those things that majoring in English, or being on the Left, or seeing yourself as a noble artist, scientist, or spiritual person can prevent you from ever getting right — to the vast detriment of your writing, politics, art, science, or spiritual practice. Money ain ‘t bad. Money is good. Restart from there and it’s no big problem, just a somewhat interesting chore, like personal health. —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;money-honey-1980-by-george-von-hikheimer&quot;&gt;Money, Honey, 1980 by George von Hikheimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the month or so since Art Kleiner phoned me to ask for a 10 year anniversary comment on my “Money, Honey”article in The Last Whole Earth Catalog, I’ve had fun diddling around modeling all the strategies I might have used following my own advice in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$30,000 invested at maximum leverage in bags of U.S. silver dimes could have been cashed in this year for $2,000,000 — that’s figuring worst case interest on the leverage and having just left it all alone to fatten the bankers whilst it fattened you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commune invested exactly that amount in 1969, but bailed out in three years to buy farmland. The farmland has not appreciated at all, at all, but we are not complaining. We’ve essentially had no money hassles. We are grateful that JFK and his co-thieves had such a delirious money policy. The Feds recently sold silver “dollars “ for 45 to 65 paper “dollars.” My. A rose is a rose but a dollar isn ‘t a dollar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second option I suggested 11 years ago made us a mere 1000% profit. Two bars of silver we bought at $1.55per ounce in 1969 were sold in 1979 for $16an ounce, less 5% smelter’s fee. With a little bit of luck we could have sold them at $50 an ounce in February, but that’s crap shooting. In silver, just follow your long term plan, using YEARS or catastrophes as your selling semaphore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn ‘t advise you to buy gold in 1970; but had youdone so when it became legal for “free “ Americans to own gold, then your money would have appreciated at an annual rate of 32.65% (this is the real return, adjusted for inflation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three best investments in the last decade have been gold, silver, and stamps. The best money investment has been Swiss francs which earned a real adjusted return of 3.7% each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honey Money for 1990
/ assume that anyone with good sense has some silver coin buried in the back 40 against the day everything falls apart and people refuse the politicians’ printed promises they laughingly call “money.” Silver on downswings is still a good buy if you don’t plan to read the financial pages and do plan to keep the silver until at least 1990 or the balloon goes up. I prefer silver to gold because of the ease of investing in it, the ready recognizability of a genuine U.S. silver dime, and the availability of small denominations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dime minted from 1916 through 1965contains .07234 of an ounce of pure silver. When silver is $49 an ounce, a real dime is worth $3.54; whereas on the historical silver/gold average ratio of 20:1 a gold Krugerrand will be around $900 — a little big to use to pay for a pound of hamburger.
The silver market has been discovered by the lemmings, and for anything other than survival or planning in decades, silver as an investment is a crap shoot — maybe a bit less honest. However, I don’t think anyone who bought silver at $40 in February, and buried it and stopped reading newspapers and digs it up in February 1990, is going to be unhappy.
Reliable Old Gnomes, Making Honey Better’n Bees&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is in 1980 no analogous madness to the insanity organized by the late sainted JFK when he decided to sell off the largest accumulation of silver in history. I have nothing as safe and wonderful as leveraged U. S. dimes to recommend in 1980.
Therefore, it’s the Swiss gnomes as your honey bees for 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that a prudent fellow could purchase an annuity through an assurance society and reliably plan his fading years in the safety and glory of the U.S. dollar. These days you might as well use toilet paper for an umbrella. In 1970 had you bought a fixed annuity of 1,000 U.S. dollars each month from a U.S. firm dealing in U.S. dollars, by 1979 you would need 700 extra dollars to keep even; but your assurance society would be paying you only the same little grand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An annuity bought the same year from a Swiss Assurance Society would be paying more than $2,600 in 1979. Your style of living would have jounced merrily upward, gilded by Swiss good sense and a commodity (gold) backed currency. There never has been a failure of a Swiss Assurance Society; the same ethics and legal protection of legal confidentiality hold as obtain for Swiss banks. There are no nasty penalties as in holding Swiss francs outright; and the downside risk is very small. With a Swiss annuity you are betting on 300 years of stability&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>A relatively unknown and thought-provoking book on primitive and vernacular forces, culture and materials that bring (brought) about their designs. Valuable and instructive for that critical factor in house design: approach.</summary></entry><entry><title>Funding</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/funding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Funding" /><published>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/funding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/funding/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-bread-game&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-bread-game&quot;&gt;The Bread Game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#do-it-right-the-first-time&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-do-it-right-the-first-time&quot;&gt;Do It Right the First Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on-free-money&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-on-free-money&quot;&gt;On Free Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-foundation-directory&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-foundation-directory&quot;&gt;The Foundation Directory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#robin-hood-was-right&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-robin-hood-was-right&quot;&gt;Robin Hood Was Right&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-seven-laws-of-money&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-seven-laws-of-money&quot;&gt;The Seven Laws of Money&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-first-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-first-law&quot;&gt;THE FIRST LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-second-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-second-law&quot;&gt;THE SECOND LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-third-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-third-law&quot;&gt;THE THIRD LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-fourth-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-fourth-law&quot;&gt;THE FOURTH LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-fifth-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-fifth-law&quot;&gt;THE FIFTH LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-sixth-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-sixth-law&quot;&gt;THE SIXTH LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-seventh-law&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-seventh-law&quot;&gt;THE SEVENTH LAW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bread-game&quot;&gt;The Bread Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re raising money from foundations, this blunt little book is indispensable. I’ve been on both sides of the breadline enough to cherish its succinct candor in the bullfart atmosphere of granting. There’s now a whole literature on fundraising, but this book was first (1973), and its forthcomingtthird edition (Fall 1980)js^ likely to still be the best. -SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wealthy Individuals. Many wealthy individuals do not have foundations of their own, but often make taxdeductible contributions to projects. There are all sorts of weird ways of finding these people: contribution reports of liberal political candidates, society pages of newspapers, friends and relatives, etc. They can be an excellent source of funds: first, because you don’t have to go through a bureaucracy to contact them; second, because they need the contact from non-wealthy people. Before you approach them, have everything together to make it easy for them to make a tax-deductible contribution to your group. Read carefully the legal and fiscal sponsor material in this book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-it-right-the-first-time&quot;&gt;Do It Right the First Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of good accounting procedures for all organizations cannot be overstated. Too many groups tend to feel that anyone can keep a set of books. Don’t be sucked into this attitude — i t can be your undoing. Keep good records f r om the beginning. Ask the help of a good accountant to at least get the books set up in good order. Even though you may write your own checks, make all your own deposits and do your own posting. Check back with your accountant every three months so that your books can be reviewed and checked over for accuracy. A good set of books will go a long way toward convincing foundations and other contributors that you are a responsible group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing Skills in Proposal Writing is written by Mary Hall, and is available from Continuing Education Publications, Waldo 100, Corvallis, Oregon 97331. This is the best, economically priced, proposal writing manual that we have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-free-money&quot;&gt;On Free Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FROM MY LIMITED EXPERIENCE, the realm of foundations and grants is one of the most cynical in the American economy, though it’s improving a little of late. Generally when you approach a foundation they are friendly and half-recep tive. They consider your project promising if a little naive, and they’d like you to write up a proposal on it. You spend a month learning how to write proposals and a month writing this one. They keep it six months. Your idea has died of  dry rot. Then they request that you re-write the proposal to accommodate (whatever) and it might go through next time the board meets. Do this three times, and you have died of dry rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most actual grants I know of were initiated by the donors, not the donees. The most effective way to get grant money is to be Highly Visible. 
I don’t know why foundation and government money is so often toxic to projects. Maybe because the process becomes so easily dishonest. Do me no favors, and I’ll tell you no lies. Or is it the belief that there’s such a thing as a free lunch that is the root lie? —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-foundation-directory&quot;&gt;The Foundation Directory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reference book of foundations. Gives addresses, finances, officers, purposes and activities. Foundations are listed by state, which is intelligent, since grants are usually given locally. (For non-foundation fundraising see The Grass Roots Fundraising Book, p. 394.) —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;robin-hood-was-right&quot;&gt;Robin Hood Was Right&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An inspiration and advice kit for rich kids. How to not feel bad about being born to wealth, and how to treat the burden as a creative resource for others. I’m a great supporter of private wealth — through no other means can you get really original and really radical giving in the society. This good book shows how. —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you publicly give away money, you hjuo i t f j c i the fact that you’re going to get hustled. People will invite you to “parties” that are really fundraisers; others will make it their business to get to know you on a friendly basis. You’ll receive tons of letters in the mail and occasional knocks on your door asking you to pay the rent of families facing eviction or bail someone out of jail in Peru, sponsor trips to Tahiti or support a struggling young poet. In short, you’ll be asked to f i l l an entire spectrum of heartrending and sometimes whacky needs that have nothing to do with projects you want to fund. You may wonder, “ Am I really this popular?” The answer is no. In response to this pressure, many rich people have simply disconnected the phone, closed the checkbook, and stopped giving money away altogether. There are better ways to deal with the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ways of giving anonymously are fairly simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Register a fictitious name w i th the IRS, get a Post Office box and a bankaccount in that name, and start writing checks. For your tax accountant’s purposes, the checks are written by you, but the organizations you give to will think they are from Merdley A. Scrump, or whatever name you choose. Or you can arrange for a lawyer to be your agent. He or she will make donations and sign the checks, telling the grantees they are from an anonymous client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• It is much better, however, to work out a relationship with an existing foundation or consultant. You will be working with people who are accustomed to keeping secrets and who have the mechanisms set up to channel money from an anonymous donor. One advantage of this method is that it provides you with a more effective cover. If your favorite local tenants’ union receives a grant from, say, the Liberty Hill Foundation, the group will think of it as a grant from the Foundation itself, even though they may be t o ld it is a “donor-specified” grant. On the other hand, if the same group suddenly gets a check from Merdley A. Scrump —who is not in the phone book and is not known by anyone — or from a lawyer representing an “anonymous donor,” that’s an open invitation to start trying to find out who the mystery person might be. A visible passion for secrecy mainly attracts publicity, as Howard Hughes and the CIA have discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important caution: resign yourself to the fact that partial secrecy is impossible. You cannot expect to give money to organization A in your name, tell them “don’t say it was from m e / ‘ and expect your secret to stop there. It ne&amp;gt;^ w i l l.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-seven-laws-of-money&quot;&gt;The Seven Laws of Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ex-banker Michael Phillips — also ex-director of POINT, the foundation that publishes this Catalog and gave away the million bucks that we got from sales of the Last Catalog — tells all. It’s a bit New Age, but it’s wise, smart, and original on a subject that usually fights those qualities. The book has made a lot of people cheeky enough to try stuff, and it’s helped them get away with it. (See his “Four Illusions of Money,” p. 288.) ^_^ —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-first-law&quot;&gt;THE FIRST LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do i t ! Money Will Come When You Are Doing the Right Thing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-second-law&quot;&gt;THE SECOND LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money Has its Own Rules: Records, Budgets, Saving, Borrowing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-third-law&quot;&gt;THE THIRD LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is a Dream: A Fantasy As Alluring As the Pied Piper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-fourth-law&quot;&gt;THE FOURTH LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is a Nightmare: In Jail, Robbery, Fears of Poverty&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-fifth-law&quot;&gt;THE FIFTH LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You Can Never Really Give Money Away&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-sixth-law&quot;&gt;THE SIXTH LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You Can Never Really Receive Money As A Gift&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-seventh-law&quot;&gt;THE SEVENTH LAW&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There Are Worlds Without Money&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money, which represents the prose of life, and which is hardly spoken of in parlors without an apology, is in its effects and laws, as beautiful as roses. 	—Ralph Waldo Emerson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you open a checking account, open it with the largest amount of money you possibly can. I’m not kidding! Even if the average balance in your account is only going to be $50, t ry to borrow a friend’s $10,000 home payment for one day so you can use it to open your account.  You don’t have to go that far, but anything over a couple of thousand dollars looks good. You can withdraw most of the money a few days after the account is opened. Really! The reason for this is that the bank records your opening t)alance on your signature card (and often in other places, too), believing that it is representative of your financial status. I did a study when I was a banker and found absolutely no correlation between opening balances and the kind of balances that appeared later on in the same account. It’s such a strong tradition to do i t this way (at least a hundred years old) that bankers still judge people by their opening balance. Try it; the branch manager will smile on you forever more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re asleep and dreaming, that’s a world without money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of foundations gone wild occurred recently. I funded Margo St. James to organize a prostitutes’ collective to protect street prostitutes from the inhuman daily abuse they get from the police, the courts, and hypocrites. I advised her to let a few local foundations know what she was up to so they would be aware of her project if in the future she should need to go to them for funds. I read the letter she sent to them; no request, just a friendly letter saying what she was doing. One liberal foundation. Pacific Change, invited her over to lunch and grilled her cruelly and mercilessly the same way they do groups they regularly screen. They berated her for not being serious, not being a member of a minority and not being poor enough. Fortunately, she told them to go to hell and left. Another foundation simply sent her a letter of rejection, although she hadn’t applied for money. These institutions are examples of how most foundations are so structured that they become numb in the process of dealing with the pain people feel in the donor/grantee relationship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>A relatively unknown and thought-provoking book on primitive and vernacular forces, culture and materials that bring (brought) about their designs. Valuable and instructive for that critical factor in house design: approach.</summary></entry><entry><title>Energy</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/energy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Energy" /><published>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/energy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/energy/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#explaining-energy&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-explaining-energy&quot;&gt;Explaining Energy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#energy-earth-and-everyone&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-energy-earth-and-everyone&quot;&gt;Energy Earth and Everyone&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#advantages&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-advantages&quot;&gt;Advantages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#disadvantages&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-disadvantages&quot;&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#soft-energy-paths&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-soft-energy-paths&quot;&gt;Soft Energy Paths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#energy-for-survival&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-energy-for-survival&quot;&gt;Energy for Survival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#energy-future&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-energy-future&quot;&gt;Energy Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#soft-energy-notes&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-soft-energy-notes&quot;&gt;Soft Energy Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;explaining-energy&quot;&gt;Explaining Energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just that, and very well done, too. I recommend it highly not only to the outsider, but to the insider as well. The various controversies seem to be fairly dealt with despite the publisher being the Berkeley “Rad Lab.” I’ll nominate this paper as the best introduction to the subject I’ve seen so far Lee Schipper is a man to watch; his work is seen more and more often where people are trying to find the facts needed for good decisions. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;energy-earth-and-everyone&quot;&gt;Energy Earth and Everyone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is very different from any other energy book we know of, in that it not only explains, but quantifies and prescribes. If energy is your interest, you really should have one of these at hand. The new 1980 edition brings the contents up to date. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nitinol has a seemingly unique property for a solid metal: it bends easily when cooled and springs back to its original shape when warmed. This “shape memory,” or ability to resume an original shape after being deformed, can potentially be harnessed for power. One scheme for such a purpose developed by Ridgeway Banks at Lawrence Radiation Laboratory in Berkeley, uses the unique physical characteristics of nitinol in an engine. The engine is a spoked wheel with 20 u-shaped stripes of nitinol hanging from individual spokes. When the wheel is lowered into a round pan divided into semi-circles of hot and cold water, it begins rotating because one set of wires are cold and go limp, while the others — those passing through the hot water — “ f i r e “ with a piston like motion, thereby driving the wheel around. Power output of this first prototype has been measured at .23 watts. This type of engine could make use of numerous sources of waste heat, as in nearly all current power production plants and other natural sources that previously have been unsuitable for tapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;advantages&quot;&gt;Advantages&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no direct fuel consumption with a nitinol engine (though heat is “consumed”).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are no by-products from the power production — such as air or water emisisions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;disadvantages&quot;&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current nitinol engines have low power output.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Engines are only at prototype stage; there is as yet no information on size limitations and capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7776 Odums’great contribution has been “net energy accounting,”called “energetics.” The idea is, you check how much energy goes into mining oil shale or into making a solar collector and compare that with the energy output. Many such energy “sources” turn out to be energy losers rather than gainers. (By such accounting the most efficient solar collectors by far turn out to be plants.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using their elegant notation for energy cycles, you can convince even politicians of the hidden wisdom or unwisdom of various energy paths. Since 1973 we have been given an energy X-ray of our economy by the historic events around oil pricing. This book and Howard Odum’s more technical and earlier Environment, Power, and Society are the kindly doctor showing what the X-ray means and what to do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of energy, this book is about how to think. (The Odums’ ideas about information — “high quality energy” — are not as convincing.) —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solar heating of houses and water uses much fossil fuel indirectly in the installations. Solar heaters have been used for a long time in sunny climates. Figure a and b compares a solar water heater and a fossil-fuel water heater. In this case solar energy is being used to make low-quality heat energy. In sunny climates, using some sunlight along with fossil fuels, energy is saved by solar heaters as compared with electric and gas water heaters. However, solar heaters use much more fossil fuels than solar energy when they are compared on an equal-quality basis (fossil-fuel equivalents). No net energy is yielded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capital costs at the start are high in terms of money and energy; savings are obtained later, after the heater has run for several years. One unanswered question is this: Would more energy have been saved if fossil fuels had been put into something else rather than into solar water heaters? As the energy for required materials becomes more costly, technology for solar heating will also become more costly. One concludes that there are ways to conserve energy using solar technology, but solar technology is not a source of energy for running our economy generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;solar water heater and (b) fossil-fuel (gas) water heater. Numbers are thousands of Calories per year (fossil-fuel equivalents). (Zuchetto and Brown, 1975.) Both systems use fossil fuel indirectly to supply and maintain equipment. The solar heater takes more equipment but uses less fuel directly. The fossil-fuel heater involves less equipment and storage and less depreciation but requires the purchase of fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soft-energy-paths&quot;&gt;Soft Energy Paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amory Lovins is one of the good guys if you t\appen to be anti-nuclear and pro-environment. But to many economists and other conventional wisdom freaks, he is a pie-in-the-sky type given to Utopian, emotional oversimplifications. I find his simplifications to be the result of crap-removal, and his arguments to be essentially reasonable if humanity is to last much longer. His discussion of nuclear matters is particularly enlightening. I’ve noticed that his noisiest foes are the emotionalists these days; Mr. Lovins is the one with the documentation. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People do not want electricity or o i l , nor such economic abstractions as “residential services,” but rather comfortable rooms, light, vehicular motion, food, tables, and other real things. Such end-use needs can be classified by the physical nature of the task to be done. I n the United States today, about 58 percent of all energy at the point of end use is required as heat, split roughly 23-35 between temperatures above and below the boiling point of water. (I n Western Europe the low temperature heat alone is often a half of all end-use energy.) Another 38 percent of all U.S. endtise energy provides mechanical motion: 31 percent in vehicles, 3 percent in pipelines, 4 percent in industrial electric motors. The rest, a mere 4 percent of delivered energy, represents a// lighting, electronics, tele-communications, electrometallurgy, electrochemistry, arc welding, electric motors In home appliances and in railways, and similar end uses that now rego/re electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;energy-for-survival&quot;&gt;Energy for Survival&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about the first analysis of Big Industrial Society energy use tobe noticed by the conventional institutions, this comprehensive overviewremains one of the best and most useful. Starting with basic thermodynamic principle, Wilson proceeds to explain what part energy plays in our society, and what the probable result will be if we continue our wastrel ways. He concludes with a look at probable and possible ways of producing and conserving power. This book was an eye-opener when it first appeared and it still is if you are not well versed in these matters. The documentation is formidable. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason heat pumps are not in wider use today is twofold: First, the reputation of unreliability has haunted the electric heat pump since its premature introduction on the commercial market in the 1950s. Additionally, since the improved heat pumps have become available, virtually no attempts have been made nationally by elect r ic utilities, manufacturers, or retail outlets to inform the public of their superiority — or even of their existence. This blackout of advertising is astounding in the light of the heat pump’s remarkable efficiency and the fact that the Initial cost of central home heat pump installations are rarely more than 10 to 20 percent more expensive than those of conventional central air-conditioning systems. Assuming the higher operating expense of home electric heating equipment, it is quite possible that heat pumps are cheaper in most areas than the combined cost of a central air-conditioning and heating system; and the operating costs of the heat pump will save an average of two thirds of the yearly electric power bill — while using one thirdithe energy of the common electrical resistance heating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;energy-future&quot;&gt;Energy Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prestigious Harvard Business School adds its establishment voice to the call for an energy conserving solar society. A perfectly straightforward cold-blooded economic case is made in support of this view, using the accepted form but not (surprise) the expected conventional wisdom information sources. The arrival of this book has lent a certain credence to the work of other authors such as Amory Lovins whose work has not necessarily been accepted in high places. It’s a good job. It even reads pretty well. It is a big help to those attempting to convince the powers that be. —J. Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already by mid-1977 there was a national de facto moratorium on the purchase of nuclear generating equipment in the United States. As a consequence, the 1979 outlook for nuclear power in the United States is much different from what it seemed to be in the wake of the 1973-74 OPEC actions. Actually, since the early 1970s there have been successive downward revisions in projections of future installed capacity in all of the Western o i l - importing countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an energy conference in Los Angeles, the oil people told the heroic story of tapping Alaska’s North Slope; the nuclear people talked about advanced nuclear technology; the coal people discussed synthetic fuels and slurry pipelines. The engineer from Los Angeles’ Department of Water and Power then stood up to explain how it got the residents of Los Angeles to go along with an effort that substantially reduced consumption of electricity: “We advised citizens to do such things as shut their curtains at night.” Here was a conference devoted to the great energy crisis, the moral equivalent of war, and here was a man who was saying that the solution is for people to do such bold things as close their curtains at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why, when an aide to one of the most powerful senators on energy issues was asked why the distinguished legislator has never given a speech on conservation, the aide replied, “ I t would either be filled with platitudes or so specific that everybody’s nose would fall into his Rice Krispies.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soft-energy-notes&quot;&gt;Soft Energy Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friends Of The Earth (FOE) has, among its many enterprises, a division called International Project For Soft Energy Paths. Among the names on the masthead is Amory Lovins, as you might expect from the name of this newsletter. Soft Energy Notes started as a Xerox stack of interesting papers but has now graduated to being a real magazine. It’s one of the most informative around, and because of the considerable travels of Mr. Lovins and the network connections of the other editors and contributors, the contents reflect the forefront of current thought, analysis, and even hardware upon occasion. Many’s the time I’ve added luster to my reputation by quoting from this worthy paper. Your subscription helps finance FOE too. —J, Baldwin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One principal work makes conventional wisdom out-of-date. That is the normal looking, cheap, even frumpy house built by Eugene Leger in north-central Massachusetts. Based on a computer-generated, Lo-Cal design, Leger’s house demonstrates that a low cost residence, with no striking design constraints, can operate in Massachusetts’ severe climate with a winter heating bill of less than $10 per month ($38.50 for January through April, or 11.5 GJ over 2.144 Celsius degree days). This performance level sets a high standard for other designers to match in economics, comfort, design flexibility, and environmental side effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is remarkable about Leger’s house is that there is nothing solar about it: it has windows on the north, east, and west sides, and no huge expanse on the south side. It does not contain tons of concrete, piles of rock, or walls of water as “thermal mass.” So how does Leger perform his low-energy trick? With a superb building “envelope”: extra-thick insulation combined with painstaking efforts to reduce air leaks. Leger placed a continuous overlapping sheet of polyethylene on the exterior walls and ceiling. To avoid breaking this air and vapor seal with electrical outlets and plumbing, he installed a newly developed surface-mounted electrical system called the “Gould Electrostrip”. This device is an important part of Leger’s energy-tight design, demonstrating how innovations in one sector can spur advances in another.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>A relatively unknown and thought-provoking book on primitive and vernacular forces, culture and materials that bring (brought) about their designs. Valuable and instructive for that critical factor in house design: approach.</summary></entry><entry><title>Corporations</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/corporations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corporations" /><published>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/corporations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/corporations/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-inside-the-organization&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-freedom-inside-the-organization&quot;&gt;Freedom Inside the Organization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#of-acceptable-risk&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-of-acceptable-risk&quot;&gt;Of Acceptable Risk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-strip-mine-handbook&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-strip-mine-handbook&quot;&gt;The Strip Mine Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#medical-nemesis&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-medical-nemesis&quot;&gt;Medical Nemesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#council-on-economic-priorities&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-council-on-economic-priorities&quot;&gt;Council on Economic Priorities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#human-fahrenheit-inhuman-celcius&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-human-fahrenheit-inhuman-celcius&quot;&gt;Human Fahrenheit, Inhuman Celcius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#stop-metric-madness-t-shirt&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-stop-metric-madness-t-shirt&quot;&gt;Stop Metric Madness T-shirt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#games-mother-never-taught-you&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-games-mother-never-taught-you&quot;&gt;Games Mother Never Taught You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#privacy--how-to-protect-whats-left-of-it&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-privacy--how-to-protect-whats-left-of-it&quot;&gt;Privacy — How to Protect What’s Left of It&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;freedom-inside-the-organization&quot;&gt;Freedom Inside the Organization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people who work for large institutions are aware of the fact that for 40 hours a week they are deprived of many Constitutional Amendment rights. This book examines the issues and begins the long 20 - 40 year battle ahead of us to bring civil liberties to the institutionalized employee. —Michael Phillips
At Connecticut Mutual Life Insurance Company, a worker can get a free lunch by sitting at an executive’s table in the cafeteria and taking part in a rap session where no questions are out of bounds.
•
In England, reports business writer Nancy Foy, the president of a large process company made significant changes in operations after he began sitting down with employees, leveling with them, and listening at length to their most devastating criticisms of management. Despite lack of cooperation from middle managers, the interchange led to significant changes in production and personnel policies, with the company going from a static, break-even level to a very profitable one.
•
In 1974 the Wall Street Journal reported that Combustion Engineering, its management incensed by a Journal article describing certain terms of nuclear power contracts negotiated by the company, was requiring officers and employees to submit to lie detector tests. “Do you know anybody at the Wall Street Journal?” was one question asked by the polygraph operator. “Did you give any information to anybody at the Wall Street Journal?” was another.
•
According to Ralph Nader, a U.S. Senate study in 1974 estimated that between 200,000 and 300,000 lie detector tests are administered each year in companies. Nader also reported that two surveys showed that the loyalty of about one worker in every five is checked by eavesdropping or other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;of-acceptable-risk&quot;&gt;Of Acceptable Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How safe is that bag of Barbeque Potato Chips? Who says so? Has anyone checked? Have the studies been scientifically valid? Have the results been suppressed? Has anyone tested for interactions with other foods? Does anyone care? This disquieting book tells what’s being done and what should be done. What will be done is up to us as citizens. I found the lack of emotional cause-hustling refreshing. There should be more research done. This tells why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-strip-mine-handbook&quot;&gt;The Strip Mine Handbook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1977, after a ten year battle, the federal Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act became law. As a result, the notorious abuses involved with strip mining coal are now controlled by the new Office of Surface Mining (OSM), a branch of the Interior Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Handbook is done so well it could serve as a model of its kind. It takes a technical subject, and an even more complex set of federal regulations, and makes them comprehensible to the average concerned citizen. How to spot, document, and report violations, and the entire grievance procedure, from an OSM inspection to a federal court suit, are superbly summarized. Since all the tough language in the world means nothing if there is no enforcement, citizen participation is going to be crucial to the success of the new law. —Richard Nilsen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acid water (low pH) is caused by the exposure of pyrite to air during the mining process. Pyrite is often contained in the rock which makes up the overburden. Acid is one of the most damaging pollutants. It kills fish and other aquatic life, eats away metal structures and destroys concrete, and increases the cost of water treatment for power plants and municipal water supply and renders the water unfit for recreational use. Low pH also causes other pollutants (such as iron) to become soluble and these in turn cause more damage. Thousands upon thousands of miles of streams have been degraded by acid mine drainage and runoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;medical-nemesis&quot;&gt;Medical Nemesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High tech medicine is making us sick, not well, and the essence of that sickness is passivity. Overblown industrialism shames traditional methods of healing, education, locomotion and social organization. Exporting the monster model plunges traditional cultures into a hopeless abyss of underdevelopment and condemns them to ecological insanity. Human abilities to self heal, indeed to self sustain, have been traded off for or expropriated by Big Brother’s quasi-benevolence. Illich, fatalistic, says that to regain control of our health, we will have to re-learn how to suffer pain; to regain our autonomy we’ll have to forfeit our “envious, greedy, and lazy”dreams. (See more on Illich, p. 40.) —Stephanie Mills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing and irreparable damage accompanies present industrial expansion in all sectors. In medicine these damages appear as iatrogenesis [disease caused by treatment]. latrogenesis is  clinical when pain, sickness and death result from medical care; it is social when health policies reinforce an industrial organization which generates ill health; it is structural when medically sponsored behaviour and delusions restrict the vital autonomy of people by undermining their competence in growing up, caring for each other and aging, or when medical intervention disables personal responses to pain, disability, impairment, anguish and death.
•
In many a village in Mexico I have seen what happens when social security arrives. For a generation people continue in their traditional beliefs; they know how to deal with death, dying, and grief. The new nurse and the doctor, thinking they know better, teach them about an evil pantheon of clinical deaths, each one of which can be banned, at a price. Instead of modernizing people’s skills for self-care, they preach the ideal of hospital death. By their ministration they urge the peasants to an unending search for the good death of international description, a search that will keep them consumers forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;council-on-economic-priorities&quot;&gt;Council on Economic Priorities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most effective checks on American corporate mischief is this non-governmental research organization. Their reports have earned such confidence that they are routinely transmitted through the economic pages of the New York Times, Wall St. Journal, etc. What the reports detail is the actual anatomy of corporate activity in terms of pollution, worker’s rights, defense contracts, relations with South Africa, energy, pricing, political activity, etc., etc. Credit is given where it is due and blame likewise. A quiet, pointedly effective service. —SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single most dramatic development in this year’s annual meeting season is the submission of a large number of anti-nuclear resolutions by individuals and groups around the country. No other single topic has provoked such a large number of resolutions from such a wide variety of individual filers. Thirty-three nuclear-related resolutions have been filed so far, up from six last year. Undoubtedly the Three Mile Island accident, which came in the heart of last year’s annual meeting season, played a major role in triggering this tremendous upsurge in shareholder actions. The high votes received by last year’s nuclear resolutions (all over 5%, five of the six qualifying for resubmission) almost certainly encouraged more submissions. Moreover, the National Council of Churches, after a three year energy policy study, has for the first time taken a formal stand opposing the use of nuclear power, resulting in the filing of 1 5 anti-nuclear resolutions by church groups for the first time this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-fahrenheit-inhuman-celcius&quot;&gt;Human Fahrenheit, Inhuman Celcius&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April first, 1794: the French National Assembly adopts the Celsius temperature scale, giving it an official relationship with the Metric system, though of course providing it with no rational one. The scale as adopted is an upside-down version of Andres Celsius’s 0° boiling point of water and 100° melting point of ice calibration. Is the legislation’s timing an obscure example of Gallic humor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copenhagen, 1708: A young instrument maker, Daniel Gabriel Fahrenheit, meets with astronomer Ole R0mer to discuss thermometers. The century prior to their meeting has seen countless experiments with a bewildering and sometimes ludicrous variety of tubes, pots, gauges, ethers, and wines that have failed to produce a.single thermometer that is both accurate and consistently reproducible. Rimer’s experiments have shown the necessity of exact calibration and the use of unvarying points to measure from, and Fahrenheit subsequently devises a method for producing a mercury-filled thermometer tube of constant diameter and two fixed points (originally body temperature and the melting point of ice, the former soon replaced by the boiling point of wateri ), a method which is the basis of all thermometer fabrication today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His instruments win him wide acclaim and a steady income, allowing further and more extensive research. He is an artisan, not a scientist,^ his shrewd good sense unconstrained by the dogma of his day. He discovers properties of super-cooled water, the effect of barometric pressure on the boiling point of water, and refinements in hygrometer construction. These are significant achievements, but perhaps no more important than the fundamental assumption that the Fahrenheit scale should have an immediately perceivable relation to the human physicality. To do this he had recorded extremes of temperature for Europe and bracketed the 0°to 100° section of his scale with them. This range is appropriate for habitable climates, and stands as an elegant reference point for temperatures outside ordinary human experience, as found in inhospitable times and places (the poles, deserts, sun, space, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This significant 0 to 100 range, unfortunately misused in the Metric system, is best suited to highdefinition measurements which can be conveniently divided by ten and which “peak” at one hundred. Thus we have a hundred dollars, miles, years, or degrees of temperature indicating significant amounts. Measurements requiring numerous divisors and/or which bear no innate relation to one hundred have other ranges, thus twelve inches, feet, months, eggs, hours, or sixteen ounces or four quarts. In general, arbitrary, person-made sums can be referred to conveniently, some of the time, by tens and hundreds, while interface with the world favors more fractionable systems, the more simply to describe portions or multiples of a given value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fahrenheit scale belongs, of course, in the former category. It is a high-definition system of great humanness, immediately understandable and easily used, since its “metric section” relates specifically to humans, and not just the characteristics of water. Unlike the Celsius scale it is a reflection and extension of ourselves; it does not have the effect of squeezing us into a sterile, high-tech worldview, residents of a minus 15 to 40 degree niche, a fraction of scale having little to do with our daily lives. •&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stop-metric-madness-t-shirt&quot;&gt;Stop Metric Madness T-shirt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In bright rainbow colors on 100% cotton, this is the most remark-provoking T-shirt you can wear. Little old ladies come up and warmly agree with you. Strangers open conversation. Even the rare metric proponent is delighted to see this hidden issue addressed in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against 75% citizen opposition or disinterest, some American multi-national corporations, some government bureaucrats, and some educators are trying to sneak metric into general usage. (“Sneak” is the word used by an avid metricizer on the California Metric Conversion Council with me. She isn ‘t kidding. She and one cohort alone managed to get the California Education Department to require exclusive use of metric by California schools from kindergarten to fourth grade. Hearings did not support the move. The press did not report it. It’s a repeat of the New Math disaster.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quietly in schools and quietly in government. Many federal bureaucracies now require metric specifications in contracts with private industry. The Department of Defense is moving toward 100% metric (when a costcutter took metric out of the MX missile specs, it saved $25 million). Nothing in the press on this either. Metric conversion has never been voted on in any nation, province, or community in the world. Proponents know&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it would Ipse. Except for specialized uses in scientific abstraction and technological micro-measure, metric is an inferior system to customary measure. This T-shirt is a vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a market democracy such as the U.S., metric has no chance to become the standard measuring system. What is possible however is being manipulated part way so that we are left hanging with an eternally confusing and alienating “dual system.” This is what happened in England, which balked half-way in, with dual direction hostility to match. The same is now happening in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former scientific proponents of metric have withdrawn their support. Good liberals are now embarrassed by the issue. You can head off the whole thing by complaining at school (British school kids, trained exclusively in metric, have to be re-trained to customary measure when they look for jobs); at any propaganda from the government directed at you through newspapers, radio, bank clocks, etc; and at gas stations, some of whom are trying to sell gas by the liter (worth boycotting on this one is Shell Oil, who is putting the pressure on the
other companies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do schools and governments fall for ideas like metric and nuclear energy that make sense so long as you don’t think about them for more than 30 seconds?-SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;games-mother-never-taught-you&quot;&gt;Games Mother Never Taught You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning and applying Harragan’s information is tantamount to “cracking the code” of business success. Most women need to approach big business as though it were foreign territory because until recently it was — only men were allowed into the policy-making ranks. Harragan makesa superb spy, and her book explains the jargon and system of the corporate world. Reading it, you can anticipate moves and plot at the same informed level as yoerr male colleagues who usually have absorbed the basic strategic information as part of their upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harragan emphasizes the fact that corporations are modeled after the military and women must understand this model to function in any business. She also dissects the myth of “sleeping yourway to success” and the myth that “goodperformance equals success.” Why didn’t we have this book ten years ago? It would have saved me and my women business colleagues from reinventing the wheel! Read it now, and you’ll have the opportunity to invent a new game or at least succeed at the old one. -Anne Kent f^ush&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you’re at your salary research, if you discover that a man who held your job previously got paid more than you or that a man doing substantially the same work as you (never mind his t i t l e , the job functions are the key) is getting paid more, don’t go home in fury and frustration. Pick up the phone book, look under U.S. Govern- Tnent, Department of Labor, Wage and Hour Division. Call up and ask about the simple process to file an Equal Pay Complaint. No one will ever find out because this agency, which enforces the Equal Pay Act, operates in secrecy and confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve slept with your boss, you’ve ended your upward mobility in that company — and the reason has nothing to do with sex. That particular career path is closed because you violated the chain-of-command relationship. I’ve even seen this happen to men who were close friends when the subordinate man failed to observe the mandated deference and distance required once his friend became his boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody knows that long-time affairs between secretaries and their bosses can go on without repercussions, always providing the woman remains in her subservient, noncornplaining role of the dutiful doormat. Those sexual relationships are possible because secretarial jobs have no place in the hierarchy; as presently constituted, they are extraneous servant positions. A secretary has no upward mobility and the job Is not a team position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;privacy--how-to-protect-whats-left-of-it&quot;&gt;Privacy — How to Protect What’s Left of It&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A traveller’s guide to the Mystery Land out among the credit bureaus, government computer systems, and new lie detector technologies. This is the definitive reference book on potential privacy invaders and what effects they could have on your life. It will either calm or confirm your fears; more likely both. The tone is a bit Naderishly self-righteous, but that’s preferable to the paranoid cynicism of most of its competitors. Each chapter ends with a list of what you can do to protect yourself — mostly raise hell, gently but relentlessly. —Art Kleiner&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you suspect that your telephone is being monitored, make sure that you can find a motivation for someone to do this to you. Is there family disharmony? Are you involved in political action? Would you be perceived as a threat — using the broadest possible stretch of the imagination — by a government agency or a political opponent? Do you belong to an organization that interests the FBI, the Department of Defe^nse, or local police? Would your employer suspect you of leaking information or cheating?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, t ry to prove that information learned by someone else could have come only from telephone conversation on your telephone. One way to do this is to talk deliberately about false (but believable) information on the telephone you suspect is being monitored. Then watch where the informationtsurfaces. If you continue to do this, you may have much more fun than discovering the physical evidence of the surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="construction" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>A relatively unknown and thought-provoking book on primitive and vernacular forces, culture and materials that bring (brought) about their designs. Valuable and instructive for that critical factor in house design: approach.</summary></entry><entry><title>Power</title><link href="https://cordesign.github.io/3/power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power" /><published>2016-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://cordesign.github.io/3/power</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cordesign.github.io/3/power/">&lt;section id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot; class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-book&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Contents&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;drawer&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-craft-of-power&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-craft-of-power&quot;&gt;The Craft of Power&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#transcending-the-power-game-the-way-to-executive-serenity&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-transcending-the-power-game-the-way-to-executive-serenity&quot;&gt;Transcending the Power Game: The Way to Executive Serenity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#action-from-govt&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-action-from-govt&quot;&gt;Action from gov’t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#congressional-hit-record&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-congressional-hit-record&quot;&gt;Congressional hit record&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#thoughts&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- /#table-of-contents --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-craft-of-power&quot;&gt;The Craft of Power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An astounding treatise on the naked wielding of naked power — how to get it, hold it, use it. Appearing more brutal than it is (Siu’s bottom lines reflect on compassion and nobility), the argument proceeds from a torrent of Machiavellian aphorisms to instruction and anecdote. If you have a talent for power, this book may set it resonating. If you have no taste for power, you’ll find that out more quickly here than in the polite corridors of the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siu is the author of the Tao of Science ip. 29), a translation of the I Ching, and other works. He has been head of numerous research departments for the U.S. military. This book is the first of a trilogy on leadership. -SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seasoned bureaucrat is adept at servo-bureaucrato viscosity: to every challenge there is an equal and frustrating viscosity. He dwells in the nirvana of historical momentum; reversing a bureaucrat is tantamount to reversing history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accommodate to the bureaucrat; he will then ease your life and extend your power. But do you otherwise; he will then drive you out of office and out of mind. People are to be used like fuel in the furnace of power, or cleared away like worn-out gears for more efficient replacements.
So that they burn with the requisite intensity, cleanse them of incombustible allegiances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcending-the-power-game-the-way-to-executive-serenity&quot;&gt;Transcending the Power Game: The Way to Executive Serenity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sequel to The Craft of Power is as benign as the other book is fierce. It consoles, congratulates, advises balance and pace, even gives practical guidance about eventual retirement. Where before Siu was talking about his bosses, here, one senses, the old Chinese gentleman is talking about himself. He speaks thus comfortably and with authority from the longest, soundest bureaucratic tradition on Earth. Badly needed ginseng in headlong America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annealing of an act into a gracious one requires a certain all-absorbing attention on the recipient, a certain sincerity of forgetfulness of oneself, a certain fitness to the fineness of the moment, and a certain genuineness about it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person travels farther, lasts longer, and acts more equably if he taxes himself at a fraction of his capabilities. Because of the resulting large reserve, he is not apprehensive over possible emergencies. His body is not fatigued and his mind not numbed. He dwells in the midst of difficulties, feeling no despair; brings his goals within ready reach, regretting no rewards passed over. There is no need for sycophancy before superiors, nor abuse before subordinates. His is an easy-going discipline, a genial demeanor, absorbing attention. He induces an airiness of festive calm. His presence is a pleasance. Cruising is prerequisite to t he life of graciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creature in pain is more pain than creature. To remove the pain is to restore the self. There can be no greater good than that a man or beast be given back his self. Let the reduction of suffering be the foundational expression of your relating to others on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you plant for a season, plant budgets. If you plant for a decade, plant reorganizations. If you plant for a century, plant people.
Let the cadre prove its selfless commitment and offer up their persons as signed undated blank checks in your strongbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not place undue weight on that course of action promising maximum gain, if successful. Limit the choices to those preventing a fatal blow to yourself, no matter what the opposition may feasibly do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credibility is the greatest obstacle to many an overture to power.
Repeat your thesis often, for people tend to shun the unfamiliar and embrace the familiar. Use phrases mellifluous to the ear, for people like to identify with the pleasant. Make it sound vital, for people incline to align with the important. Announce your intentions to accomplish something, which is actually well on the way. Promise something that seems difficult but is within ready reach of your unseen reserves. Then let the people conclude for themselves that you are truly a man of your word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propitiousness There is nothing more important in imparting elegance and style than the art of being propitious. The essence of propitiousness is good timing. More failures in the exercise of power have been due to poor timing than any other single factor. When Catherine the Great ascended the throne she tried to introduce the liberal ideas of Charles de Montesquieu.
But the Russian state of mind was not receptive. Her ministers balked, and the peasant uprising of Emilien Pugachev of 1773 forced her to drop the idea. It took another 120 years before the time was ripe for even a semblance of parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our own day, there are relatively few executives who possess a really keen sense of timing. Most of them do not know how to use the instrument of time. They are unable to allow precisely for lead time, lag time, incubation time, time to build up a head of steam, time to forget, time to get bored, time to stop talking, and so on. They do not have the feeling for matching the duration of different acts to come into fruition against their respective times of need. They fail to lay the basis for the resolution of conflicts before their actual onset. As a result, they only struggle with the fortitude of facing crisis after crisis. They never glide with the art of de-existing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;action-from-govt&quot;&gt;Action from gov’t&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found that one of the best ways to get anything out of the national government is by writing directly to your congressperson; the best way to gain results with a state agency (unless you have an unusually good state representative) is through a letter to the governor’s office, although this approach may vary from state to state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;congressional-hit-record&quot;&gt;Congressional hit record&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note to pragmatic existentialists: no matter how whole your particular earth, there’s always somebody in Washington that wants to deal it away. Protect yourself with the Congressional Record. A bit windy but you’ll learn “how to read it with a little practice. And burns slowly with good heat for after use in the fireplace. Write your Congressman and Senators first, to see if they can add you to their comp list. If not: $75 per year, 50 cents per copy, payable in advance. Check or money order payable to Superintendent of Documents, Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C. 20402. Well worth the investment. ^&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It used to be said that the only safe political behaviour (nevermind one’s pronouncements) was to be economically liberal and socially conservative. Jerry Brown reversed that formula, made it work, and it’s becoming the new conventional wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collection of remarks, chosen from the press by poet Lawrence Ferlinghetti during the first year or so of Brown’s governorship of California, conveys the freshness of thought he brought to a stale game. The special appeal of the man, besides his intelligence, is his willingness to learn before your very eyes and include you in the process. – . - -SB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be very reluctant to approve of spending which does not require basic  undamental structural reforms wherever possible, because just pumping more money into the machine is not going to turn around the very difficult situation that we face in the schools. If you look at the reading scores, look at the achievement scores, talk to kids, talk to teachers, there is something wrong in the classroom. Now much of it reflects a certain malaise in the society, and I don’t really hold the teachers accountable because of the failures of the system. It’s a problem for those in government and those in a position of responsibility to make the changes. I’d like to see some changes. And when people come for the money, that’s the opportunity to make the change. If you just give it away without requiring this kind of change then you lose an opportunity. I don’t want to see that opportunity lost in the event we can make some constructive changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an elephantiasis that takes over that you get so big you can’t function. I think if you look at the classical world, as the political entity expanded its role and responsibility, it ran into problems both in Greece and Rome that it could not handle. And it was accompanied by these generalized and mystical feelings that as the borders expanded, as the discipline weakened, as the decadence increased, as the classes that were in the leadership position lost their nerve, then those on the perimeter ultimately came through. In 410, when Mr. Alaric walked through, where we had this wonderful civilization, there was grass and wild dogs wandering around. That is not, you know, a lesson that is ignored with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they [politicians] would just kind of jump out for a while, and then maybe come back. But they stay long beyond their time. The Greeks had that — ostracism. Ostragon is the potsherd that’s dropped in the pot. If the majority drop it in then you’re out. There was a fellow named Aristides the Just. Aristides the Just was going through his ostracization process, and he stood there and as some Athenian came by to drop in the potsherd which was an indication for him to exile, Aristides said’, “Why are you doing that? Haven’t I been a good man?” And the Athenian said, “Look, we’re tired of hearing the name of Aristides the Just.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s a certain amount of truth to that . . . once in power, no one ever likes to give it up. Because it becomes addictive. It becomes co-terminous with your own identity with yourself, and so i t becomes very hard to shake loose from. So all this detached philosophizing, but when the moment of separation comes, I suppose . . . they say they throw you out or carry you out. But I think it’s probably good to make it a relatively brief period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to do things. Maybe by avoiding doing things you accomplish quite a lot. Maybe i f Kennedy had avoided the Bay of Pigs or Vietnam, that would have been quite an accomplishment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="power" /><category term="J. Baldwin" /><category term="portable" /><category term="tools" /><category term="toolbox" /><summary>Siu is the author of the Tao of Science ip. 29), a translation of the I Ching, and other works. He has been head of numerous research departments for the U.S. military. This book is the first of a trilogy on leadership.</summary></entry></feed>
